<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faith by which we are justified, in scripture-sense according to Scripture, opened, explained, and applied, on Rom. 5, I : in six sermons.</title>
            <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15714076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15714076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1179:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faith by which we are justified, in scripture-sense according to Scripture, opened, explained, and applied, on Rom. 5, I : in six sermons.</title>
                  <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Marshal ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published as preached with little or no alteration at the desire of some of the hearers."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Bright by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans V, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Justification.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104490:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104490:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FAITH BY WHICH We are Juſtified, IN <hi>Scripture-Senſe:</hi> According to <hi>Scripture,</hi> Opened, Explained, and Applied, on <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. In Six Sermons. Publiſhed as Preached, with little or no Alteration, at the Deſire of ſome of the <hi>Hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eſaiah. 55. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Ho every on that Thirſteth, come ye to the Waters, and He that hath no Money, come ye, Buy, and Eat without Money, and without Price.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Marſhal,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104490:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104490:2"/>
            <head>THE FAITH BY WHICH <hi>We are Juſtified, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Firſt Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 5. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>INtending to Treat of <hi>Faith, whereby we are Juſtified,</hi> I have taken this Weighty Text, as the Foundation of the Diſcourſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have theſe Four remarkable Points concerning Faith, as we are Juſtified by it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. This plain Point firſt comes before us, <hi>That we are Juſtified by Faith,</hi> expreſſed thus, <hi>Being Juſtified by Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That we are <hi>Juſtified by Faith,</hi> is a concluſion reſulting from a ſtrong nervous and vehement Reaſoning of the Apoſtles, that had gone before in the foregoing Chapters, ſignifyed in that Particle, <hi>Therefore,</hi> aſſuring to us this great Truth.</item>
               <item>3. The Bleſſed conſequence of being Juſtified by Faith; <hi>we have peace with God, the Judg of all;</hi> This gives full Peace, Reſt and Quiet to Conſcience, <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance for ever,</hi> according to the Nature of a full and perfect Righteouſneſs.</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104490:3"/>
               <item>4. The ſupreme Principal Cauſe of our being <hi>Juſtified by Faith,</hi> and having Peace from it, is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; by whom, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle goes on, we have acceſs unto this Grace, wherein we ſtand.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This then is the grand Propoſition of the Apoſtle. That being <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, we have Peace with God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall at this time, therefore, propoſe to open the great Grace of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Faith to you, by which we are Juſtified; becauſe, indeed, it is one of the greateſt Points that can be ſpoken of; And therefore, theſe Heads of Diſcourſe, I will now undertake to handle to you concerning it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſhew you that the Supreme and Higheſt, and Original Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or Deſcription of <hi>Faith,</hi> is to be taken by its Relation to Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator. And it is nothing at all, if you remove that; If you take away that Reſpect, that great Reſpect, that it looks upon, and Eyes Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I ſhall come to conſider, how Faith, even in its relation to Chriſt, and as it looks upon him, is ſaid to be <hi>Juſtifying Faith;</hi> or that whereby we are Juſtified.</p>
            <p>For, if we did not rightly ſtate this, as the Goſpel doth (as it is ſaid) the laſt Error might be worſe then the firſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore I would particularly guide your Thoughts and Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, how Faith, as it looks to Chriſt, Juſtifies. I ſhall therefore ſhew you, that it is not Faith it ſelf, but only the great Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> received by Faith, that <hi>Juſtifies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Third place, I ſhall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> conſider that great certainty that <hi>Faith</hi> is to obtain in every point wherein it ſo Acts, which it ought to reach after, and to aſpire to, in every point wherein it hath to do with Chriſt, that we may have Peace by it, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 17. 7, 8. <hi>They have ſurely known, and have believed, that I came forth from thee, and that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> So in every thing <hi>Faith is ſurely to know.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p>In the Fourth place, I ſhall ſhew you the Life, and the Power, and the Activity of this Faith; and compare thein, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and <hi>James</hi> 2: where that Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Faith being Dead,</hi> that is without Works. And I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you, that there is no ſuch Commentary, no ſuch way of Reconciling the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Faith Juſtifying without Works;</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaking that a Man is not <hi>Juſtifyed by Faith only, but by Works alſo.</hi> I ſay the great Reconciliation will be, by laying <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and <hi>James</hi> 2. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>Now I begin at this time with the firſt of theſe; And I'll lay down, with great aſſurance, this Aſſertion, concerning the reſpect Faith hath to Chriſt; That there never had been ſuch a thing as the ſound of <hi>Faith</hi> in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104490:3"/> the World; there had never been the Name; Not the Air; and much leſs, the Thing; had not God <hi>brought the first Begotten</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>into the World.</hi> Had not <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> given a <hi>Being to Faith;</hi> there had never been ſuch a thing as <hi>Faith.</hi> And therefore it is very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the Apoſtle calls Chriſt by this very Name, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 23. <hi>Before Faith came</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we were under Tutors and Governors; We were kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, ſhut up unto the Faith, which ſhould afterward be revealed. Before Faith came.</hi> It is certain <hi>Faith</hi> was in the World before the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> before the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> For, it is ſaid, <hi>Abraham was Juſtified by Faith;</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> believed God, and it was imputed to him for <hi>Righteouſneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and yet, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>before Faith came,</hi> that is, <hi>before Christ came;</hi> becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> is ſo Eſſentially Dependent upon Chriſt, and Reſpective unto him. Chriſt is ſuch a real Foundation and ſupport of <hi>Faith;</hi> that he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily and properly called by the very Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, or by the word, <hi>Faith,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Faith came.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the clearer opening and making out of this to you, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon theſe three Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the higheſt <hi>Revelation of God.</hi> Now <hi>Faith,</hi> it is deſcribed by almoſt all (in part, at leaſt) to be an Aſſent to a <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> upon the Credit that we give to the <hi>Revealer;</hi> upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Veracity, and Certainty of the Truth of the <hi>Revealer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, <hi>Faith,</hi> you know properly, is a believing the Report of another, or the Witneſs of another. We cannot properly be ſaid to <hi>Believe,</hi> when we do know the thing our ſelves, and have ſeen it by our own Eyes; but when we Truſt and Credit that Aſſurance, that another gives us of it.</p>
            <p>Now therefore I ſhall endeavour to make out to you, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is He, <hi>Faith</hi> muſt needs Live and Die with him (as I may ſo expreſs it in familiar Language (it is as Eſſential to <hi>Faith</hi> to have the Manifeſtation and Revelation of Chriſt, as it is for the Eye to have Light. And then,</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Second</hi> place, Whereas the notion of <hi>Faith</hi> is a Truſt, and a depending upon ſome great Good that is offered to us, from the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Good; that we have no Right nor Title to, in our ſelves. I ſhall ſhew you that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is that Great and Rich Good that is giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to us from the Father. And that tho we have no Right to the thing in our ſelves; yet we come to Truſt, and to Depend, and to Rely upon it, as if we had a Title. And then,</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third</hi> Place, Whereas Faith is very truely, tho not in the firſt Account of it, deſcribed to be a Power of Holy Life, and Holy Action: And a Man believes no more, than he is truly and really transformed by into the thing that he Believes. I ſhall ſhew you, That <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> is that great principle of <hi>Holy Life,</hi> and of <hi>Heavenly Life,</hi> that doth impower the Souls of his People, according to the degree of the preſent State;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104490:4"/> and ſhall bring them to that ſpotleſs, to that blemiſhleſs ſtate, in the Glory of his Appearing.</p>
            <p>I begin with the <hi>Firſt</hi> thing, and that is to ſhew you, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is that <hi>great Revelation</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> hath Primarily, Principally, Originally and Supremely to cloſe with, and to give up it ſelf unto.</p>
            <p>You ſhall find in the 3d of <hi>John,</hi> that this is a Notion of Faith; and a Notion of Faith proper to the great <hi>Revelation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> ſaith <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 10. <hi>He that believeth in the Son of God, hath the Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in himſelf. He that believeth not God, hath made him a Liar, becauſe he believeth not the Record that God gave of his Son.</hi> The great Record that God hath given, it is of his Son; that he hath given his Son as the <hi>Great Mediator;</hi> as the <hi>Great Redeemer;</hi> as the <hi>Great Sacrifice;</hi> as the <hi>Great Righteouſneſs</hi> of the World: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d therefore, if any Man does not believe this, <hi>he has made God a liar.</hi> God hath done all in the Goſpel, that can be done, to give us an Aſſurance of it: So it is the great Revelation. And ſo, when our Lord ſaith, <hi>They have ſurely known, and believed that thou didst ſend me:</hi> It is the very ſame thing, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the great Saviour and Redeemer of the World. For, what's the meaning of God's ſending Chriſt, but a ſending him as a Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>or? As you may find plainly John 3. 17. <hi>For God ſent not his Son into the World to condemn the World; but that the World, through him, might be ſaved.</hi> And, <hi>Him hath God the Father Sealed,</hi> John 6. So that from all this, it is moſt Evident that it is the great Revelation. And tho this be a great Truth, yet ſtill the Goſpel raiſeth it higher. And I beſeech you, that you would ſeriouſly conſider; when a Man Believes in Jeſus Chriſt, he does not only believe a written Word; I deſire again your ſerious Attention to it: He does not only believe a written Word; he does not only Believe a great Teſtimony from God, or a ſound of words concerning it, but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the word himſelf</hi> comes to him. Indeed it was heretofore in a manifeſtation in the Fleſh: But the very ſame thing is now manifeſted by the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt. And by his coming in Spirit, he comes as that <hi>Word of the Father;</hi> as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Word of the Father:</hi> And he ſhews himſelf to the Soul; he ſhews himſelf in Spirit to the Soul; ſo that the Soul Believes the Word of God; becauſe Chriſt, the word of God ſhews himſelf to him. And we never have the Truth of Faith, till we have this very coming of the Eternal Word to us. As you ſee (1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1.) how the Apoſtle ſpeaks concerning this word, <hi>That which was from the Beginning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our Eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of Life. For the Life was manifested, and we have ſeen it, and bear Witneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you.</hi> Now pray, Why does the Apoſtle declare this? Not that you ſhould reſt in a written word: That's the thing I would deſire you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Not that you ſhould reſt in a ſound of Words; but that ye alſo <hi>may have fellowſhip with us;</hi> (ver. 3.) <hi>and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:104490:4"/> 
               <hi>and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Not that we ſhould expect any Viſional Repreſentations of theſe things: That's not the Intention of it. But that we ſhould look for a real Manifeſtation of the Father, and the Son; or of the Father by the Son, and through the Son: And alſo of the Son by the Father. So that there is certainly. a Sight of Chriſt; I ſay, a ſight of the Son, in Faith. And if we did but thus conſider the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Faith; indeed, I cannot but apprehend, there could be no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Chriſtians, and Chriſtians, in theſe points concerning Faith; and ſo concerning Juſtification; if we had but true and right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Faith. It is true indeed, there's a great deal of falſe Faith, of counterfeit Faith, that has never ſeen Chriſt. But all true Faith, it hath ſeen Chriſt; it hath come up to the very word of Jeſus Chriſt: That is, to Jeſus Chriſt the Word So, <hi>John</hi> 6. 40. there muſt be a ſight of the Son, before there can be a believing in him. <hi>And this is the the will of him that ſent me, that every one, which ſeeth the Son, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him, may have everlaſting Life.</hi> And therefore, as I told you, he is called the <hi>Word of God;</hi> that is, the Eſſential and Eternal <hi>Word of God,</hi> manifeſted in Fleſh; manifeſted in Human Nature. And There is no ſight of Chriſt without his coming to us, without our receiving of him, by the Teaching of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father, and by the manifeſtation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And ſo ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> when it pleaſed God to Reveal his Son in me. You ſee here is not only words, either Spoken or Written; but there is the very Son himſelf Revealed in us. I do acknowledg all this is in a Spiritual Senſe, not only in an Intellectual Senſe: Tho it is true, That ſhall be Subſervient, and as it were the Conveyance and Vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of this ſight. But it is a Spiritual Sight, wrought by the Power of God, and by the Spirit of God. And O therefore! This is the great Point I would preſs upon you. And indeed, I have taken notice that the moſt Spiritual Writers, and Preachers of Faith, They have ſaid, <hi>That Faith is upon the Perſon of the Son; the Perſon of the Eternal Word in our Nature, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It does not deal firſt of all with his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and Salvation that comes by him; I mean, principally: I don't ſay, but God may draw a Soul firſt by the conſideration of his Benefits. But the principal Touch of Faith, it is upon the Son of God. I might give you innumerable Scriptures that verify this great Truth. And I deſire that we may take notice of it. In that forenam'd place, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 8. Chriſt ſaith, (this is the point) <hi>They have believed that all things whatſoever thou haſt given me, are of thee; and that I came forth from thee, and that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> All this, Chriſt ſays, you may ſee, immediately concerns the Perſon of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. So in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> a place that is worthy our notice; and that I ſhall have occaſion of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual recourſe to, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20, 21. <hi>I am Crucified with Chriſt: nevertheleſs I live; yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me.</hi> I urge it here only, to this purpoſe, to ſhew you, that Faith, it immediately goes out to the Perſon of Chriſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104490:5"/> even in the point of Revelation. This is, That, it principally goes on and touches there cloſeſt and faſteſt; upon the very perſon of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O therefore, that our Souls now might find ſomething of this going out to the perſon of Chriſt! A Tender of the Perſon of Chriſt to us; that Jeſus Chriſt the Word would come, and ſhew himſelf to us! That in a Spiritual ſenſe, we might ſee him with our Eyes, and handle him with our hands; we might have all aſſurance of a real Union, of a real Touch betwixt Chriſt and our Souls.</p>
            <p>And then I would deſire you to take notice alſo of this; that when this great Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt hath come in, and has a Reception in the Soul; then all the Truths that flow in along with him, they come in alſo into the Soul; and the Soul receives, according to all the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and Jeſus Chriſt it receives all Truth, when this great Revelation hath firſt of all entred, and taken place in it. All the Truths of God, they come in by Jeſus Chriſt; as he is ſaid to be The Truth; and the Son of the Father in Truth. It is a very great conſideration, this; no Truth is indeed truly taken in, till Chriſt is taken in. If you would but apprehend this; I confeſs there are many Learned, and Wiſe, and Great Men in Diſcourſe; they inſiſt very much upon the Proof, by Natural Demonſtration, Argument and Reaſon of the Being of a God. I am very far from Detracting, or Derogating from what they do: For it is very worthy in its own kind and place. But this I do aſſure you, that there's no man in the whole Univerſe, that hath taken in truly the Knowledg of the <hi>One God;</hi> But he hath taken it, in and through Chriſt, and by Chriſt: Or elſe, he hath it not ſavingly, if he hath it not in, and through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So there are great Arguments to Diſtinguiſh between Good and Evil; the Law, and Natural Conſcience go far in it. But, I aſſure you, no Man has taken in any of the Principles of Natural Conſcience, in a ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way, till he hath taken in Jeſus Chriſt. All Truth, it comes in by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1. 17. The Evangeliſt there, hath it expreſly, <hi>The Law came by Moſes,</hi> ſaith he. There was a meaſure of Light given by the Law: But (ſaith he) <hi>Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And I'll give you one great Scripture, that will make this very plain, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. Saith the Apoſtle there; <hi>Without Faith, it is impoſſible to pleaſe him: For he that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is.</hi> A great many of the Ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts that are in this very Age, at this very time carry it, as if they would not thank the Goſpel (as I may ſo expreſs it) they are ready to ſay, they would not thank the Revelation of it for the Proof, that there is a God, that is, <hi>One God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, as it may be true in their ſenſe too; that is, It is Demonſtrable by the Light of Nature, and by Reaſon, and by Argument, I acknowledg, with all my Heart, it is ſo; And yet, notwithſtanding, I ſay, no man that ſavingly believes that there is a God; But he that doth it by that Faith, that hath taken in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104490:5"/>
            <p>And therefore, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If any Man hath not the Son, he hath not the Father.</hi> If he doth not come to the Knowledg of the Father, by the Son; he hath not the true, and the right Knowledg; the true E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical, Spiritual, ſaving Knowledg, ſo much as of a God.</p>
            <p>So, concerning Eternal Happineſs and Miſery; there may be great Light of Truth offered, from Natural Argument.</p>
            <p>We never come to ſee, and know Truths indeed; till we come to know them by the Eternal Word; that word of God coming in to us, who is (the) Truth.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I beſeech you, That you would retain theſe things in your Minds and Judgments; and that you might be able, when you hear Diſputes, concerning <hi>Faith,</hi> and concerning <hi>Juſtification</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> that you would remember, that this is the true excellency of <hi>Faith, To touch the Perſon of the Son of God; to come to Him, to ſee Him, to be united to Him, as the Great Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, all the Truths that we have, in the Word of God; they are All of great Excellency, and of great neceſſity: But they all Centre in Chriſt (the) Truth; who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (the) Truth. They Centre in him, who is (the) Truth; they are all but Lines flowing from him, and Return to him. I know, every one will eaſily grant, that the Knowledg of the Angels is much greater than the Knowledg of any Man; or of all men put together. Now you ſhall find, that the Angels, notwithſtanding the great Orb of Light that they make, or are; notwithſtanding they are great Intelligences; yet notwithſtanding, the Knowledg of Chriſt, is the Supreme Knowledg that they have, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>To the intent that now unto the Principalities and Powers in Heavenly places, might be known by the Church the manifold Wiſdom of God, according to the eternal purpoſe which he purpoſed in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> Eph. 3. 10, 11. And therefore indeed, tho Angels and Men were Created with very large meaſures of knowledg (I make no doubt) and excellency of an Intellectual Being; yet, that God hath ſo ordred things; that the great Knowledg, the great Manifeſtation of his manifold Wiſdom, ſhould come in by Jeſus Chriſt, that hath given occaſion to ſuch wonderful Explication of that Infinite Eſſential Truth, <hi>That God is.</hi> I ſay, it hath given the occaſion: That indeed, I may ſay, there had never been ſuch a thing as <hi>Faith;</hi> that is, an higher underſtanding than Natural Underſtanding is; a greater Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Truth, than all Natural Comprehenſion of Truth is.</p>
            <p>O Infinite Treaſures of Truth, that will be found to have flown from the bringing in of Jeſus Chriſt the great Mediator! This is that which hath broken up the great Deep of Truth; I ſay, the great Deep of Truth is broken up by the Manifeſtation of Chriſt: The great Cataracts (as they call them) of Heaven, are opened by this very Wiſdom. The great flowings in, and Cataracts of Truth have flown by the Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104490:6"/> of Chriſt. Indeed, I am not able to conceive the greatneſs of this Truth, or to ſpeak to you. How greatly Rich will Heaven, and Saints and Angels be made, by knowing this great Truth of the Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt! And therefore, it is not Truth Rivetted into their Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Underſtandings; But it is properly called Faith; tho indeed, all Truth will be Demonſtrated ſo really in the Future State, that it will make that kind of Faith to ceaſe, that is an Evidence of things not ſeen; tho it may ſtill properly be called <hi>Faith;</hi> in regard of that Infinite Knowledg Flowing from God, through Influence by and in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So I have ſpoken of the Firſt Head I propoſed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> thing I would therefore open to you, is, <hi>Faith</hi> doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly adhere, and run to ſome good that is offered: And eſpecially, under a ſenſe of Danger, and a ſenſe of great Ruin and Miſery, if there be not extraordinary Reſcue; And therefore this is the Second thing I aſſert, That there had never been that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Truſt;</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Refuge;</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Reliance;</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Dependance,</hi> if Jeſus Chriſt had not been made known: For, What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Jeſus Chriſt, but the great Deliverer? As the Apoſtle ſpeaks in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. laſt. <hi>He that Delivers,</hi> ver. 10. It is not, <hi>Delivers us:</hi> But he is the, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Deliverer;</hi> his Name is the general Deliverer. Who is <hi>(The) Deliverer;</hi> even Jeſus Chriſt, Stiled and Surnamed; made notably known to us, by being <hi>(The) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer</hi> from the Wrath that it to come. He is <hi>(The) Deliverer</hi> from the wrath that is to come.</p>
            <p>So I ſay, There had never been Footing for <hi>Faith,</hi> if it had not been for Chriſt; becauſe of that great Good. And indeed, as I have often declared to you; ſo I am poſitively of that Judgment, that the Elect Angels did fly to Chriſt, even as we do, in a loſt and undone ſtate: So they to be ſecured from that loſt State, the Fallen Angels and Man-kind run into. I make no doubt, they found all Created Beings ſtood in themſelves too ſlippery, and too ready to fall: And they thought it ſafeſt to be under the Wing of the Mediator, to be within the everlaſting Arms of the Mediator.</p>
            <p>Therefore much more, if God had not given this great Saviour to loſt Man; this great Deliverer; this great <hi>Ranſom;</hi> this great <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> this great <hi>Righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God;</hi> there had been no Room for the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Truſt;</hi> for the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Relyance</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men.</p>
            <p>You know, oftentimes in ſcripture, Faith is ſpoken of, as truſt: That when a Creature does not know what to do; nor whither to run; It runs to God, by Faith. Now, this is all founded in the abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that we all have, to fly to Chriſt for Redemption, being loſt and undone without him.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104490:6"/>
            <p>And therefore you find all ſcripture agrees to it, that we are under a neceſſity to come to him, as the <hi>greateſt Good</hi> that can be <hi>offered</hi> to us. Chriſt is that greateſt Good that can be offered to us. Even <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> Life from <hi>Everlaſting</hi> to <hi>Everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>therefore,</hi> obſerve the vein of <hi>Scripture:</hi> It is indeed, ſo much, That I need not almoſt name ſuch things to you, <hi>John.</hi> 13. 14. <hi>As Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes lifted up the Serpent in the Wilderneſs, even ſo muſt the Son of Man be lifted up: That whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have Eternal Life.</hi> It is very plain, what our Lord here intends. We are under the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that they that were bitten with the <hi>Serpents</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> that died <hi>immediately;</hi> they ſwelled, and died, and broke in pieces <hi>immediately,</hi> if they had not the Remedy in this Braſen <hi>Serpent.</hi> And ſo we are in the ſame <hi>Condition:</hi> Our Thigh would Rott, and our Belly would ſwell (to allude to that <hi>Repreſentation</hi> under the Law); I ſay, the Thigh; That is, the <hi>Soul,</hi> and the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and all the <hi>Powers of the Soul,</hi> they would preſently be <hi>Gangren'd,</hi> (in a ſpiritual ſenſe) and give up to Ruin and <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> were it not for Jeſus Chriſt. And ſo again, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>For God ſo loved the World, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That very word, ſhould not periſh, it is as much as to ſay, he ſhall <hi>certainly</hi> periſh, if he does not come to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> If he does not believe in him. And <hi>v.</hi> 36. <hi>He that believeth on the Son, hath everlaſting Life: And he that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Son, ſhall not ſee Life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> As Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah ſaith, <hi>He that trusteth not in the Lord, he ſhall be like a barren Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſhall not ſee when good cometh. So, he ſhall not ſee Life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Wherever he goes, <hi>the wrath of God abides on him.</hi> Though he be Rich, and happy in the world; yet ſtill he does not know what a <hi>Companion</hi> he hath with him: The wrath of God going along: And what a Roof, and what a skie he is always under? what a <hi>Canopy</hi> of Heaven he is under? The wrath of God abides on him, Dwells over him.</p>
            <p>So, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life; and he that hath not the Son of God, hath not Life.</hi> And therefore here is Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, Reliance upon him, the Faith of Truſt. Jeſus Chriſt is he that hath brought in the Faith of Truſt.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid it to you before; and I ſhould never be afraid to ſay it to a Congregation of the Learned'ſt and Wiſeſt in the World; That the Angels fled to Chriſt, foreſeeing poſſibility of Ruin, if they ſtood upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>But we are upon a plain, and Confeſſed, and Acknowledged neceſſity; we had never had ſuch a thing as Faith, if God had not offered, and given, and made known his Son to us, as a Redeemer.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104490:7"/>
            <p>Now, I would deſire you to Conſider; That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> never came to any <hi>Soul,</hi> with his Benefits: And not come himſelf. He doth not ſend his Benefits, and not come himſelf. Which is the thing, I would very fain, in every thing, preſs upon you. I ſay, he never ſends his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, but he always comes himſelf. <hi>I am the way, the Truth, and the Life. I am the Life, ſaith Chriſt. And he is Redemption, ſaith the Apostle</hi> Paul. <hi>He is (the) Redemption. There is not a Redemption ſeparate from him: But he is our Redemption; and he is our life; and he is our Ranſom; He is our Sacrifice; He is our Redeemer; He is our Mediator; He is our All.</hi> And therefore Faith, It hath to do with the Perſon of Chriſt. Indeed, it may be very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to hold out; and is certainly, abſolutely neceſſary, to hold out the Benefits of Chriſt. But we ſhould take heed of this: For here comes in a great deal of diſpute and wrangling, who ſhould have the Benefit of his Righteouſneſs by his Blood. Alas! This is not the thing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, but we are to come to the very Perſon of Chriſt, and to unite with him; <hi>who loved us, and gave himſelf for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, It is not a diſputable thing, how we ſhall have his Benefits; If we pitch firſt upon him by Faith, and by his coming into us, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in us; and we in him; As I ſhall after ſhew (if the Lord give oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) that our Juſtification is by union. There is no Juſtification, but by union. It is not by what we do; or what Conditions or Terms of the Goſpel we obſerve; Though they ſhall more effectually follow, than any other way we Diſcourſe of. I don't ſay, that there is no need of Repentance, of Faith, and holineſs of life. But, our Juſtification is immediately flowing from union, and no other way; As I hope, by the aſſiſtance of God, and his Goodneſs giving leave, evidently to make out by <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore pitch upon that, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. to ſhew you, that <hi>Faith</hi> flyes with all the ſpeed it can for <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, who have <hi>fled for Refuge, to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us, verſe</hi> 18. who have fled. All the ſpeed they can poſſibly make, is little enough; too little (as it were) to lay hold upon that <hi>Hope</hi> that is ſet before us, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>I deſire to be found in him.</hi> The Expreſſion evidently alludes to that Expreſſion in Scripture, when the <hi>Man ſlayer</hi> fled from the <hi>Revenger;</hi> when the Purſuer of Blood, and the Miniſter of Vengeance was at his Heels, he made all the way he could, <hi>to fly to the City of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</hi> So I ſay, the Soul by <hi>Faith,</hi> makes all the way it can, with all the ſpeed it can, to flee for Refuge to the Hope ſet before it, in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I would argue another thing to you, as I did in the former; as I told you, All <hi>Truth</hi> comes in by the Knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Great Truth.</hi> All the Report of <hi>Truth</hi> comes in by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>ſupream Truth.</hi> So all Truſt, and Hope of <hi>Good</hi> comes in the <hi>Great Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104490:7"/>
            <p>As now, ſuppoſe a Man be in want, or in fear of Danger; or in fear of this or that Inconeniency in the preſent State: Why <hi>Faith,</hi> this <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> having taken him in, as the great <hi>Redeemer;</hi> as the great <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> it flies to <hi>God</hi> through him, in every Caſe.</p>
            <p>As now, It was certainly a Fruit of <hi>Saving Faith</hi> in <hi>David,</hi> when he ſaid to <hi>God, I flee to thee to hide me from danger; when my Heart is overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Lead me to the Rock, that is higher than I.</hi> I make no doubt, but this was a Fruit of <hi>Saving Faith.</hi> And ſo when the Servants of God cry to him for neceſſary Food and Rayment, if they have taken <hi>Chriſt;</hi> it is a Fruit of <hi>Saving Faith</hi> of that kind. When <hi>Jehoſhaphat cryed out to God,</hi> when he was likely to have been ſlain, as <hi>Ahab</hi> was; it was <hi>Saving Faith</hi> in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat,</hi> that cryed to God; why? becauſe he had taken in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if we cry to God without the <hi>Redeemer;</hi> it is but howling. But when once we have taken hold of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is <hi>Saving Faith.</hi> There's one Scripture more, (and then I'll conclude this with Application) to ſhew, when we come to Chriſt, upon a Title; when we have firſt taken Chriſt as the <hi>ſupreme Good,</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> and <hi>Deliverer,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 19. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let them that ſuffer according to the Will of God, commit their Souls to him, in well doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi> He does not ſay, a <hi>faithful Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> but a <hi>faithful Oreator.</hi> Why? becauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Redeemer</hi> had been taken in. We can never truſt in God, as a <hi>faithful Creator,</hi> till we have firſt truſted in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the great <hi>Redeemer,</hi> the great Sacrifice of <hi>Attonement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come therefore to make the Application of this, in theſe three Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; in which, I will be very brief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe is,</hi> Oh! I beſeech you, let us in every thing conſider <hi>Faith.</hi> When ever you think of <hi>Faith,</hi> don't look upon it in it ſelf, but only in its Relation to the <hi>Redeemer.</hi> Indeed, <hi>Faith</hi> is like the Eye; there is a great deal of admirable curious Workmanſhip in the Eye, as the <hi>Anatomiſts</hi> of the Eye have made very plain. One would ſtand amazed, to behold the admirable Skill of the Creator, in the Eye! that excellent Machine, as I may call it. And yet notwithſtanding all this, Without Light, what were the Eye? even nothing at all. And ſo <hi>Faith</hi> hath a great deal of curious Workmanſhip; It is a great Work of God; <hi>The Work of Faith with Power,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith. It is the Faith of Gods Power; It is the <hi>like precious Faith.</hi> But if you take away <hi>Chriſt</hi> from it, alas! It is nothing at all. All its Excellency is in its Union to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſpeak this, that I would not in the leaſt ſeem to quarrel, or to raiſe a Controverſie with any Holy Servants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Yet I ſay, we are ready to run into ſuch a kind of Notion of <hi>Faith,</hi> as if there was ſome Excellency in its ſelf; and becauſe it obeys; as it is very true, it does: And becauſe it purifies the Heart and Life, and lays Arguments and Engagements of Obedience: I don't deny any thing of this; but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104490:8"/> deſire to ſpeak the ſame thing. But I ſtill affirm, that we may not be miſtaken in <hi>Faith:</hi> For, this is not its Excellency; no more than it is the Eyes Excellency, that it is curiouſly made, whereas it would be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; no, not ſo much a beauty, if it were not for Light. It were all one, as if a Man were blind, or had no Eye. So it is all one, if it were not for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whether there were ſuch a thing as <hi>Faith,</hi> or no ſuch thing as <hi>Faith;</hi> It were of no value, or Account, if it were not for him. And therefore, I beſeech you, keep all this ſtrictly in your Thoughts, <hi>Faith</hi> is excellent: Why? becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> is excellent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it hath to do with him. It hath a great many Subordinations of Excellency on this ſide <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but its great Excellency is, it touches <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſecond Place,</hi> I beſeech you let us always mind this, <hi>the Perſon of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Don't think of his Benefits divided from his <hi>Perſon,</hi> for God gives you his Son: he gives you his Son firſt and Principally; but when he gives you his Son, all his Benefits come with him. There is <hi>Pardon, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> every thing comes in by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He gives you Chriſt himſelf firſt; It is He that is made this to us. There are ſo many Scriptures in this Point, that I don't know where to ſtay, when I come to conſider it. As now, <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life.</hi> And God gives his Son, and all things together with Him. And, we have not <hi>Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> as it were, apart, that God ſends them by themſelves, and we have them: And though <hi>Christ</hi> be to be known to be the Author only of them, it is no matter whether we mind him further or not; I ſay, this is not the Truth of the thing. <hi>But ye are of God in Chriſt Jeſus, who is made unto us Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi> And you cannot have them, except you have <hi>Christ</hi> firſt; you muſt have him firſt, and unite firſt with him. But that which I ſhall pitch upon, is <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs I live; yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the Life which I now live in the Fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> But indeed, the firſt and principal thing that we are to look to in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>Redemption, Pardon of Sin in his Blood; Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification,</hi> as I ſhall after ſhew you; and therefore we ſhould always look to his Perſon. And then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the third, and laſt place,</hi> I ſhall deſire, if we love <hi>Christ,</hi> let us love theſe <hi>Truths of Christ,</hi> and theſe <hi>Manifeſtations of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe they are gloomy; there's a great gloom upon them, you may plainly perceive, not only among the <hi>Heathens, Mahometans, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts:</hi> But there is a gloom among <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> they are not ſo clear, ſo bright, ſo lively and excellent among us, as in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: For, if theſe things I have ſpoken of, be true, It is certain, here's the Oriency of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> here's the Pearl of great Price, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And our Souls ſhould cloſe with, and cling to Him. Now, becauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104490:8"/> there is a Fog and Miſt about theſe things; how earneſtly ſhould we pray for the Kingdom of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> For, then theſe things will come into their Glory, into their Beauty; into their Perfection.</p>
            <p>And therefore, I ſay, if we love <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our Souls ſhould earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that this Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould appear. For then, (as I have often told you) the <hi>New Song</hi> ſhall be ſung, <hi>as it were a New Song.</hi> It was as it were loſt, and ſhall be recovered again; and therefore it is, <hi>as it were, a new Song.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing in the Kingdom of <hi>Christ,</hi> (I beſeech you, remember it; remember, it is ſpoken to you this day; and I hope, that many of us may live to ſee the thing) the firſt thing that ſhall be, after the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall be known, ſhall be the <hi>Voice of Harpers, with their Harps,</hi> ſo loud, as it were the <hi>Voyce of Thunder;</hi> this, <hi>As it were a New Song of the Redempiion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104490:9"/>
            <head>THE FAITH BY WHICH <hi>We are Iuſtified, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Second Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 5. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE great point of Diſcourſe that I have ſingled from theſe words, is to open to you the Nature of that Eminent and Tranſcendant Grace of the Goſpel; the Grace of Faith, which our Lord hath an eſpecial reſpect to in theſe words, <hi>John</hi> 17. 7, 8. <hi>They have known, that all things whatſoever thou haſt given me, are of thee. For I have given unto them the words which thou gaveſt me, and they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them,</hi> (that is, they have received them by Faith) <hi>and have known ſurely, that I came out from thee, and they have believed them that thou didſt ſend me. They have known ſurely; and they have believed that thou didſt ſend me. They have Believed.</hi> Knowing, <hi>and</hi> Believing, are here United one with another, becauſe of that ſure Knowledg, and that ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Faith gives to the Souls of his People. And then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Here's the great Object of this <hi>Faith.</hi> For, <hi>they have known, that all things whatſoever thou haſt given me, are of thee. Whatſoever thou haſt given me; the things are of thee.</hi> And the words which thou gaveſt me, they have received them: And they have known ſurely that I came out from thee, and that thou did'ſt ſend me.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:104490:9"/>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt is the Supreme Object of Faith, as he is one with the Father, and hath come into the World, as the Mediator and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of loſt and undone Sinners.</p>
            <p>Therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have undertaken, in the firſt Place, to make out this to you; that the proper Object of Faith, is the Mediator; and that Faith came in with the Mediator; and ſubſiſted wholly in him, and upon him. And if you take away the Mediator; Faith becomes a meer Nullity, a meer nothing. There is the ſame, and far greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction betwixt Chriſt and Faith, than there is between the Eye and Light. As you know, the Eye is nothing without Light: ſo Faith is nothing, without that great Light, the Mediator.</p>
            <p>This I began to open to you,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In that Jeſus Chriſt is the Supreme Revelation of God. For, Faith (by thoſe that ſtrictly Define it, or Deſcribe it) it is an Aſſent to Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>Now, the great Revelation of God, it is Jeſus Chriſt. He is the great Truth, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi> And all Truth (as I ſhew'd you) depends upon him. For there comes in with Jeſus Chriſt, a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth, proper and peculiar to himſelf. All the great Truths of Scripture. Indeed, there are notable Intimations, and great Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations in all the Holy ways of God, in which the Soul of Man was at firſt Created.</p>
            <p>But the great Subject of Truth; it is the Truth that comes in with Chriſt: As I ſhew'd you, he ſaith of himſelf, <hi>He is (The) Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And even Natural Truth (as I abundantly ſhew'd you) it comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt. Natural Truth; that Truth, that there is an everlaſting Being: That God is; This comes under Chriſt: It removes (as it were) from being a Natural Truth; and it comes under Chriſt. Tho it is true, there are great Arguments to prove it; yet it chooſes (as it were) and delights to come under Chriſt. And ſo the Truths of Eternity (as I ſhall ſpeak more preſently) they come under Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Second</hi> place; as Faith, it pitches upon ſome good, upom ſome grace that is ſhew'd to the Children of Men; ſo Jeſus Chriſt, he is the great object of Faith; becauſe all Good it is in him. The Promiſes of Grace, they are all in him. And therefore, that is a great Scripture, that I did not mention to you the laſt day; and therefore, I beſeech you, now to take it into great conſideration, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>All the promiſes of God are in him, yea, and in him</hi> Amen, <hi>to the Glory of God. In him, yea, and in him</hi> Amen. All that God hath ſpoken of Grace, and of good will to the Children of Men; it is all in Chriſt: All the promiſes in him are, <hi>yea;</hi> and in him they are <hi>Amen.</hi> And he is <hi>(The) Deliverer,</hi> as I ſhew'd you, from the Wrath to come. <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of Glory, Col.</hi> 1. 27. It is wonderful, how all Good is Treaſured up in Chriſt. Faith runs to a Promiſe; it runs, eſpecially to Grace; and to a Revelation of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104490:10"/> Riches of Grace: And all is in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> come now to go on.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third</hi> place, As Faith is a mighty active Power of Holineſs, and of New Obedience; ſo its whole Reſt and Truſt is in Jeſus Chriſt. As the Truſt of Faith (<hi>in whom ye truſted,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>the Truſt of Faith, in regard of Eternal Life and Salvation;</hi> ſo the Activity of Faith flows from the Mediator; And as all the Promiſes, or Hopes that we can have of God, are in Chriſt; as I ſhew'd you, they come under Chriſt, now, as the Redeemer: As I inſtanced to you, in that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>That you would</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>give up your ſelves unto him, as a Faithful Creator:</hi> That is, as a Redeemer. So it is in this point; All the Holineſs of a Chriſtian, it flows from Faith in Jeſus Chriſt. That is the true Holineſs, that comes in by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives from Chriſt; and is conveyed to us by Faith.</p>
            <p>So that if you enquire, How ſhall I come to be Holy?</p>
            <p>I do not deny, that all the Rules of the word of God, are of great help and aſſiſtance herein; But yet, ſtill I ſay, that the Centre, and the Root, and the Fountain, and the Well-ſpring of All, is Jeſus Chriſt. And therefore we find in that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. a place often to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and mentioned, when we are ſpeaking of theſe things. <hi>Of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us, Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and Sanctification, and Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is made <hi>VViſdom</hi> and <hi>Sanctification.</hi> The firſt being in a Soul by <hi>VViſdom;</hi> it is from Chriſt. He is the Wiſdom by which a Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the madneſs and folly of all the ways of Sin; and engages there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into the ways of Holineſs. Chriſt is his Wiſdom to do it. He is the Wiſdom of Faith, and the Wiſdom of Repentance: The Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by which a Soul ſeeing its loſt ſtate in it ſelf; its unholy and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſtate in it ſelf; It comes to ſay, Where ſhall I have a change of this State and Condition? And it ſees Chriſt to be the only Foundation of it. And therefore, the Power of Holineſs, it comes in by Believing; you find therefore how often Chriſt is pleaſed to ſpeak of himſelf, ſuch words, as do certainly imply the Power of Holineſs to be from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. As now, <hi>John</hi> 14 6. He comprehends all thoſe in himſelf; ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am the way, the Truth, and the Life. No Man, &amp;c.</hi> Take theſe words, either in the point of Juſtification, or in the point of Calling; or in the point of Sanctification; or, take them in the higheſt Glory of Saints: it is very true: <hi>Chriſt is the way, the Truth, and the Life.</hi> Now <hi>He is the way,</hi> in regard of Sanctification; And he hath the mighty Power of all that Life of Holineſs; of all that Life of Grace, derived from himſelf. So that indeed, when we find our Graces to be either in a declining, or in a low State; or when we find our ſelves under any Temptation, or, when we find our ſelves to be to grapple and conteſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104490:10"/> with things that Fleſh and Blood cannot tell how to conteſt with; our great Wiſdom is to run to Chriſt for Power; for the Power of Grace; for ſtrength of Grace to do it; and to depend upon him, wholly for it.</p>
            <p>For, As I ſhew'd you laſt day, That a Servant of Chriſt, a true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in Chriſt, he is Crucified with him: Even as to the point of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; he is upon the Croſs together with Chriſt; he comes under the ſentence of Guilt, with Chriſt; and all his own Righteouſneſs is is ſlain. Why ſo, in the very ſame manner, all his Luſts, they are brought under by the mighty Efficacy of Truth that is in Jeſus Chriſt: As now, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> chap. 6. you ſhall find where the great Power of Crucifying of our Luſts is. It is certainly by our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, <hi>I</hi> ſay, it is certainly the Being of the Soul in Chriſt, that Crucifies all theſe. Saith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24. <hi>They that are Chriſt</hi>'s, (pray obſerve) <hi>have crucified the Fleſh, with the Affections and Lusts.</hi> They that are Chriſts, have done it: A Man does not become Chriſts, by Crucifying his Luſts and Affections; But, becauſe his is Chriſts, therefore he has Power from Chriſt, to crucify his Luſts and Affections. This is a great Truth; they that are Chriſt's, have crucified their Luſts and Affections: Their ſinful Luſts and Affections. And in the 6th chap. of the <hi>Gallatians,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, as he ſaid before, <hi>That he was crucified with Chriſt;</hi> ſo he ſays in this chapter, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 17. <hi>From henceforth let no Man trouble me; for I bear in my Body the marks of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> And ver. 14. <hi>God forbid, that I ſhould Glory in any thing, ſave in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee here how plainly the Power of Chriſt is that, that crucifies Luſt, and crucifies the love of the World.</p>
            <p>Here is our great miſery, our great unhappineſs in the Power of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption over us; That we do not receive Chriſt. And then, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 20, 21. When the Apoſtle had ſet out the exceeding evil converſation of the Heathen; He ſaith, <hi>ye have not ſo learned Chriſt; If ſo be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the truth, is in Jeſus: That ye put off concerning the former converſation, which is corrupt, according to the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> do moſt ſincerely acknowledg, that all the Scripture, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt, and all the commands and Admonitions, and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Reproofs of it; and all the Terrible Expreſſions of it; they are all, (<hi>I</hi> do acknowledg) of great uſe, of great influence in an Holy Life. But yet it is all through the Spring, in whom they are; and thro' that mighty Power, in whom they are. And therefore we do but go down to the <hi>Philiſtines Forges,</hi> when we go in the Power of Mortification, and being crucified to the Affections of the Fleſh; when we do not look to Chriſt, as the Principle hereof: He is the Sanctification of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104490:11"/>
            <p>And ſo in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Such were ſome of you,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) having ſpoken of the greateſt ſinners: <hi>But ye are waſhed, but ye are Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but ye are Juſtified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> Abundance of Scripture might be added to this, that ſhew that the Powers of Sanctification, and Holineſs of Life, are all in Chriſt; who makes perfect in every good Work to do the will of God; and works in us that which is well pleaſing in his ſight.</p>
            <p>So that I ſay again, We do not become Chriſts, by doing theſe things; But we do them, becauſe we are Chriſts; becauſe a Power, and a Might flows from him, and from his Blood, to do it by.</p>
            <p>O that therefore, we may know the true Method and Order of being Holy! It is certainly of firſt being Chriſt's: And if we are ſtrangers to Chriſt, we ſhall be ſtrangers to Holineſs, and of all the ways of Purity, without him.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore lye under this Rich Redemption of Jeſus Chriſt, in ſetting us free from the Plague of our own Hearts, and from the evil of our Lives. And then,</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, conſider further; (for this is moſt neceſſary to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) that all the Reaſons, Rules, Meaſures, and Arguments of <hi>Holineſs; Chriſt</hi> hath brought them all under himſelf. For, that Law of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> that God planted in the Heart of Man, that Law of <hi>Holineſs</hi> that is given out every where in his Word; all that is derived from thence; it is all now come under <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and under his mighty Power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law came by</hi> Moſes; but <hi>Grace,</hi> and the Power of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> it comes by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He hath, as the Apoſtle ſaith, implanted the Law, by himſelf: And the <hi>Law is written in the Hearts of his Servants,</hi> by and through the Grace of the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> as you know that great Place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10.</p>
            <p>How comes the Law to be written in the Hearts of the Servants of God? It is becauſe of the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> of which, <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> is the <hi>Surety,</hi> and the <hi>Mediator. This is the Covenant, that I will make with the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Laws into their Mind, and write them in their Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the <hi>Holy Laws of God,</hi> they are written in the <hi>Heart and Mind,</hi> through the <hi>New Covenant;</hi> of which, you know, every where, the Apoſtle declares <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the <hi>Surety,</hi> and the <hi>Mediator,</hi> and the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator</hi> of.</p>
            <p>So that, if there be any thing that is well ſpoken, in the whole World, of Morality, it is properly tranſplanted under the Influence of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Son of <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> and the <hi>great Sanctifier of his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, if we take thoſe Places of Scripture; to be ſure, <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Sanctification,</hi> in the ſtrict Senſe, is not to be excluded. <hi>That he might Sanctifie his People with his own Blood. For their Sake, I ſanctifie my ſelf, That they might be Sanctified through the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104490:11"/>
            <p>Now, <hi>Faith</hi> is that (as I ſhall ſhew you) by which we derive from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> All <hi>Sanctification</hi> in what ſenſe ſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I come to the fourth thing,</hi> in which I would ſhew the excellency of <hi>Faith;</hi> and that it is all in and through <hi>Christ.</hi> And that is, thoſe <hi>Heroick Acts,</hi> thoſe <hi>extraordinary Acts,</hi> that the Servants of God have done in the World, at any Time; they have been done by the Power of <hi>Faith;</hi> as that Power has been received by <hi>Faith,</hi> from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. We have a great Record of thoſe things that the Servants of God have done, in the ſeveral Ages of the World; the great many things they have done; thoſe mighty Acts that they atchiev'd; as you ſee all along, in that Chapter.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle begins with <hi>Abel;</hi> and ſo he comes down to <hi>Noah,</hi> and to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> and then to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and to <hi>Moſes;</hi> and then, to the Servants of God together; as you find, <hi>verſe</hi> 33. <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and <hi>Jepthah,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> it comes down to: Who through Faith <hi>ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, wrought Righteouſneſs, obtained Promiſes, ſtopped the Mouths of Lions, quenched the violence of Fire, eſcaped the edge of the Sword; out of weakneſs, were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in Fight, turned to flight the Armies of the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens. Women received their dead raiſed to life again; and others were tortured, not accepting deliverance, that they might obtain a better Reſurrection. And others had Tryals of cruel Mockings, and Scourgings; yea, moreover of Bonds and Impriſonments. They were ſtoned, they were ſawn aſunder, were tempted, were flain with the Sword; they wandred about in Sheeps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>skins,</hi> and <hi>Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented.</hi> And theſe all, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>verſe</hi> 39. <hi>having obtained a good Report.</hi> Indeed, a good Report, are Words, in our ordinary uſe of them, too low. For, the Apoſtle means, they obtained a high Renown; for, they are words of a celebrating Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; they are of a <hi>Holy,</hi> great <hi>Fame;</hi> they obtained a great <hi>Fame,</hi> that's the meaning of it; they are ſpoken of with great Honor, in all Ages. And all this was by <hi>Faith.</hi> And their Faith, it reſted upon <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> For, as a Captain, (as he ſpoke to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who is here referred to) he appeared. Nay (ſaith he) <hi>Captain of the Lords Hoſt, am I now come;</hi> and now thus <hi>appear</hi> unto thee. It is very remarkable, that all the great <hi>Acts,</hi> that the Servants of God, have at any time done, they have done it by the power of <hi>Faith;</hi> and that <hi>Faith,</hi> in <hi>Chriſt, Joſh.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it came to paſs, when</hi> Joſhua <hi>was by</hi> Jerico, <hi>that he lifted up his Eyes, and looked, and behold, there ſtood a Man over againſt him, with his Sword drawn in his Hand; and</hi> Joſhua <hi>went unto him, and ſaid unto him, art thou for us, or for our Adverſaries? And he ſaid, nay, but as</hi> Captain <hi>of the Hoſt of the Lord, am I now come. And</hi> Joſhua <hi>fell on his face to the Earth, and did worſhip, and ſaid unto him, what ſaith my Lord unto his Servant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this we know, is not what any <hi>Holy Angel</hi> would accept. And therefore, it is certain, it was <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104490:12"/>
            <p>He fell down, and worſhipped. But when the Angel, in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was offered to be worſhipped, you know, he ſaid, <hi>ſee thou do it not, for I am but a fellow Servant.</hi> But ſaith <hi>Joſhua, What ſaith my Lord unto his Servant? And the</hi> Captain <hi>of the Lords Hoſt ſaid unto</hi> Joſhua, <hi>looſe thy ſhooe from thy foot, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground; and</hi> Joſhua <hi>did ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſpeak this only, as an evident Argument, that this was Chriſt. And it is evident, that he is the Captain of the Lords Hoſt, in any great thing that his Servants do.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when any of the Servants of God, in the old <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> did extraordinary things, it was by the Power of their <hi>Faith;</hi> and their <hi>Faith,</hi> it was a <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt. And therefore, certainly, if we had the power of Faith, there would be great things that we ſhould do.</p>
            <p>We do but very little things; becauſe we have very little <hi>Faith.</hi> But if an abundance of Faith was given to us, we ſhould be able to do the great things, that the Servants of God have done heretofore.</p>
            <p>And, when ever ſuch things, as I cannot, but upon all Occaſions, ſay to you, I hope the time is near, that great Things ſhall be done; they ſhall be done by the Power of Faith; and by the Captain of the Lords Hoſt appearing, and coming on our ſide. And, as a further proof, (if there needed any; but I think, there needs nothing more to be ſaid) The Captain of the Lord's Hoſt, was Chriſt. The Apoſtle takes that very Expreſſion; ſurely, we have Reaſon to think ſo: For, Scripture delights in its own Language, and to refer to it, and to ſpeak like it ſelf. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>For it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many Sons unto Glory, to make the Captain of their Salvation perfect through ſufferings, the Captain of the Lord's Hoſt.</hi> So that I ſay, all the great things that have been done by the Servants of God, have been done by the power of Faith. Such things had never been done, if it had not been for the Power of Faith, coming in by Jeſus Chriſt. It is certain, ſuch things had never been done, ſo as to give glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God, in the doing of them.</p>
            <p>Indeed, I know, you may be ready to ſay; why, the Enemies of God have done great things; Have we not heard, and read of great <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi> Of the great <hi>Caeſars</hi> of the World? Of the great Princes of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army! They have done great things.</p>
            <p>It is true: Becauſe (as God ſaith) they were his Servants, in the doing of them: And they were as the Axe, and as the Saw in his hand; he gave them great ſtrength. And ſo now, what is done, and has been done by the <hi>French</hi> Potentate; certainly, it is, becauſe God hath had a great End and Deſign in it.</p>
            <p>And, I am very ſure, it is well known, that God hath ſet him up, to do all that he has done, for ſpecial purpoſes of his own, and According to all that Frame of Propheſy, that is given.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104490:12"/>
            <p>But now, here's a great Difference: As here, do but obſerve it; As God ſpeaks in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> There's great difference between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar;</hi> Between <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and ſuch a one as <hi>Nebucad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar;</hi> or ſuch a one as <hi>Alexander;</hi> or ſuch a one as <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> that Hiſtory makes ſo famous. I ſay, here's the great difference. As God ſaith, <hi>They are but like the ſaw in his hand.</hi> Iſa. 10. 15. <hi>Shall the Ax boaſt it ſelf againſt him that heweth therewith? Or ſhall the Saw magnify it ſelf against him that ſhaketh it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, Theſe are things without Senſe: You know, an Ax or a Saw, whatever it doth; it does without any Senſe of what it does. So theſe have done great things; becauſe they have been in God's hand to do by: But they had no ſenſe at all of the things they did: They had no Faith: Here's the great difference.</p>
            <p>Now, I ſay, if we could receive it; this I look upon to be the great Reconciliation between the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>James.</hi> This 11th to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> it Expounds what the Apoſtle means by a Faith of Works: He does not ſpeak of the ordinary Works of Holineſs; but he ſpeaks of extraordinary. As <hi>Abraham</hi> Sacrificing his Son; and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> leaving the Int'reſt of his Country, from a ſight, that God was pleaſed to Exalt that People of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Theſe were the Heroick Acts of Faith: And theſe, the Apoſtle properly ſpeaks of.</p>
            <p>And therefore, to Argue the ordinary Duties, Practice, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and Holineſs to Juſtification; is not according to the ſenſe and intention of the Apoſtles meaning; not in <hi>Juſtifying Abraham,</hi> as I ſhall ſpeak particularly to that, wherein, and how Faith comes to Juſtify.</p>
            <p>But ſtill I go on further; Leſt any one ſhould ſay, why then, are not the ordinary ways of Holineſs, under the Power of Faith, and ſo Derived by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Yes, by all means, as I have ſpoken to you before. He is our <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> But I ſpeak of it only now, as under this Head; the Heroick Acts of Faith. For, all the ordinary Acts of Faith come under him.</p>
            <p>As now, ſuppoſe any one is called out, either as a General, in this very Age; if he be truly a Believer in Chriſt; tho he does but the things that are Accountable, according to the Law of Arms, (if I may ſo ſpeak) according to the Law of a General; and the great uſe and office of a General; yet ſtill, even thoſe ordinary Actions; where they are Believers; are done by the Power of Faith.</p>
            <p>You'll ſay, Why? when others do the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, as I did before; They are but Axes and Hammers; As God calls <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the <hi>Hammer of all the Earth.</hi> And his Empire was the <hi>Hammer</hi> of all the Earth. They do things but as <hi>Hammers.</hi> There's a great deal of difference (I'll aſſure you) in this thing; tho the outward Action be the ſame; yet the inward is not the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104490:13"/>
            <p>When a Man, as a General, leads an Army in the Cauſe and Intereſt of God; and when another does it by his own Proweſs; The one does it by Faith; the other by an Inſtrument.</p>
            <p>There is a living Spirit in Believers; and therefore God does many times raiſe them up to greater Actions than Ordinary.</p>
            <p>But I only ſpeak, when God calls Men to <hi>Deny to be</hi> the Son of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's</hi> Daughter, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he calls <hi>Joſhua</hi> to be ſo great a Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the World; And <hi>David,</hi> and thoſe Worthies to do extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Works; It is by Faith, through the Mediator: it is all upon his Account; and is managed for him and by his ſtrength, by Faith.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> thing, in which I would open to you the great excellency of the Nature of Faith; That in the obtaining of Wonderful things; it is a Wonderful thing how God hath enlarged Faith to the obtaining of extraordinary things, in ſeveral Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>Indeed, you may ſay, ſuch things are ceaſed now.</p>
            <p>But (as I have endeavoured to ſhew you) there ſhall be a Revival of them. But now, when ſuch great things as we read of, at any time, in the Scripture; Extraordinary Appearances of God, in a way of Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of his Saints. When <hi>Elijah prayed and ſhut the Heavens:</hi> When great Deliverances were obtained by Prayer, in Fights; When there has been great Anſwers of Prayer, extraordinary Anſwers of Prayer, in any caſe; That God hath <hi>Appeared in the Mount;</hi> This hath been from the Power of Faith. And therefore the Apoſtle (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11) one of the things that he puts into the great Record of Faith; it is this, <hi>That they obtained promiſes,</hi> verſ. 33. <hi>They stopt the Mouths of Lyons.</hi> When the Fire could not burn upon thoſe three, <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego.</hi> Why, this was by the Power of Faith they <hi>quenched the Violence of the Fire. And Women received their Dead, raiſed to Life again:</hi> This was by the <hi>power of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe things are extraordinary things, given to the Mediator, to do for his Servants, according to the ſeaſon that he ſees fit. And they are conveyed to. But I would very earneſtly deſire, to add ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>What is the Reaſon that the Scripture is ſo abundant of ſuch a <hi>World to come? Whereof,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>we ſpeak; In ſuch a new Heaven; in ſuch a new Earth; In ſuch a Sabbattiſm that remains for the people of God;</hi> In ſuch a glorious Inheritance as ſhall he? What is the Reaſon we are ſo hard to believe it? It is only the want of Faith.</p>
            <p>I'll give you one Scripture concerning this, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 39, 40. <hi>Theſe all having obtained a good report through Faith, receiving not the promiſe: God hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> This place of Scripture, if it were but well purſued, followed, and Argued from, would prove to you, That the great Point of Faith, is the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt. Undoubtedly, there ſhould have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104490:13"/> been an Eternal Life, an Eternal Happineſs for <hi>Adam;</hi> If he had ſtood in Innocency, There had been a preparation, and a proviſion. But this very ſtate of things comes in by the Mediator; by his entring into Reſt for us, this great <hi>Sabbattiſm</hi> comes in.</p>
            <p>But now the thing that I would urge; (I wouid help you in this) <hi>thro' Faith they obtained a good Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great Fame, (as I told you before) a great Renown. But they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the Promiſe.</p>
            <p>How can it be ſaid, They received not the Promiſe, if it be ſo, that Heaven is the Promiſe? For, I would ask any Man, that gives Reverence to this word of God; Do you Believe that <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Moſes, Samuel, David,</hi> &amp;c. Do you think they are now in Heaven? And yet (ſaith the Apoſtle expreſly) <hi>they went away out of this World, and left a great Fame and Honour, and record of themſelves, behind them; but did not receive the Promiſe.</hi> Did they not receive the Promiſe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, when their Spirits went out of their Bodies to Heaven? Can it be ſaid, They Received not the Promiſe, if Heaven were the Promiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended? And yet, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They received not the Promiſe; God having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect.</hi> Therefore I ſay, That Glorious Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt; That Viſible Glory of Saints, both in Body, and Spirit; That they did not receive: The <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>We look for according to promiſe;</hi> they have it not yet; tho they have been in Heaven for ſo many Ages. And therefore Faith is on purpoſe for this Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, among the things that are to come: Among them, I ſay; and as a Principal of that <hi>World to come, whereof we ſpeak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore add at this time, by way of Recollection (and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with Application, a recollection of all that I have ſpoken, of the great excellency of Faith. And I beſeech you, in the Firſt place, Let this be a general Poſition concerning Faith; That Faith is proper to that New Creation (from firſt to laſt) that comes in by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It is as really a New Heaven (if I may ſo repreſent it to you) a New Heaven of Grace, As that New Heaven, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſpeak of; ſhall be a New Heaven, in compariſon of that we have now. The Heaven we have now, declares the Glory of God: It is one of the wonderful Works of God: The <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars;</hi> How wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are they! And yet, for all this; there ſhall be a New Heaven. God does not like the Heaven that is now, as ſufficient to declare his Glory. For, if there had been no fault found with the Heaven and Earth that are now, what place had there been for a New Heaven? As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Argues in the Caſe of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, conſider; it is the Apoſtles own Argument, in another caſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 7. <hi>For if that firſt Covenant had been faultleſs; then ſhould no</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104490:14"/> 
               <hi>place been ſought for the Second.</hi> And in that he ſaith, <hi>A New Covenant; He hath made the firſt Old. Now that which decayeth, and waxeth old, is ready to vaniſh away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would but apply it to the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth.</hi> If there had been no fault found with the preſent Heaven and Earth; (tho they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Glory of God) what place had there been for another Heaven and Earth? For the Second Heaven and Earth? and why are they ſaid to wax Old, but that they are to vaniſh away? Surely, the Apoſtles Argument is very Subſtantial, according to the Diſcourſe here. But the thing that I intend it for, is, juſt as the New Heaven, and the New Earth, that God will make; juſt ſuch is the Faith that God hath brought in; That great Grace of Faith; It is as New, as the New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the New Earth. It is a way of Salvation; a way of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; a way of Holineſs; a way of Eternally making Happy, As new, as the New Heaven, and the New Earth. And therefore it is no wonder that Men boggle at Faith ſo; and that they make ſuch a ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; and are ſuch Enemies to it; That no Diſcourſe that is found in the Goſpel, will pleaſe them, or ſerve their turn: It is becauſe God hath Created a New thing. It is not of the Firſt Creation; but a New thing; Grace of a New Erection, of a New Extraction. O Bleſſed are they that have it! For, it is as much above Nature, as the New Heaven, and the New Earth ſhall be above the preſent Heaven, and the preſent Earth. It is prepared and fitted on purpoſe, by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</p>
            <p>To give it you in another Expreſſion: And, I beſeech you, reſt upon it; And that you may have it ready to Diſcourſe, when any Aſſail the Doctrine of Faith; that you may have it <hi>fitted within your Lips,</hi> as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, Juſt as the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> exceeds the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Firſt;</hi> juſt ſo does the way of Faith exceed the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and uprightneſs of <hi>Adam,</hi> in the Firſt Creation, wherein he was Created.</p>
            <p>You'll ſay, How can you make this appear? There is a plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for it: I appeal to all the World, upon this Scripture, againſt the greateſt Enemies of Faith. <hi>Therefore it is of Faith, that it might be by grace; to the end, that the promiſe might be ſure to all the Seed,</hi> Rom. 4. 16.</p>
            <p>As much therefore, as Grace excels the Righteouſneſs of Man in his firſt Creation; ſo much does Faith excel all Natural Power.</p>
            <p>And, as the certainty of Grace excels that of our Doing; So much does Faith excel the Firſt State in which Man was Created. For, <hi>It is of Faith, that it might be by Grace. And then, that it might be ſure; It muſt be of Grace.</hi> I ſay therefore, I beſeech you, conceive right of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Faith, by what I have ſpoken to you, out of this very Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 16. And have it in your Mouths, as that word of Truth,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104490:14"/> by which you may Anſwer any that Reproach the Holy Doctrine of Grace, and Faith in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But I would add but briefly, of the Excellencies of Faith, wherein God hath magnified Faith, above any other Grace. And yet, I ſhall ſhew you, in the next Diſcourſe (if the Lord will give me leave to do it) that notwithſtanding all this excellency of Faith; It cannot in the leaſt be ſaid, to Juſtify by it ſelf; but only by that hold it has of Chriſt, and of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. But, I ſay, at the preſent;</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, here's the excellency of Faith; That Faith hangs only upon God, and Chriſt, and that which is Divine, and Eternal; it will not venture upon any thing that is Created. And if you come once to true Faith; you hang only upon God and Chriſt, and the Spirit of God. A great deal of difference, when a man hangs by this, and that Title, that he thinks is well grounded, and is in himſelf, and in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>He has nothing then of Faith: For, Faith hangs wholly upon God, and Chriſt, and the Spirit, and Grace, and what is Divine and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p>In the Second place; Faith, it gives all the Glory to God; It muſt needs do ſo, when it hangs all upon him; gives Glory to God, and Chriſt, and Grace; Gives Glory wholly to him, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. You know, <hi>Abraham was ſtrong in Faith, and gave glory to God.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p>In the third place, It acknowledges all to God back again. It gives Glory to him in the Action. That, that I mean now is, ſetting to the Seal, that God is true; depending upon Infinite Grace, Infinite Power. And then, when the thing is done, it returns all back again to God. <hi>To him be Glory that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb; who Loved, and Waſhed in his Blood;</hi> To the <hi>Holy Spirit, as ſeven Spirits before the Throne.</hi> It returns all to him. And then,</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, It Receives, even to Eternity, by way of free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication from God, and from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore, tho there be ſome kind of Faith (I acknowledg) that fails (as the Apoſtle ſaith) and ceaſes, in the Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs of Eternity, and of the Kingdom of Chriſt; ſome kind of Faith doth.</p>
            <p>But yet that Faith whereby the Spirits of Saints, even to Eternity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Glory, and Bleſſedneſs, and Life from God, and from Chriſt; That Faith never fails.</p>
            <p>I am very aſſured, when Saints have been ten Thouſand, Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Ages in Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs; They'll own it ſtill, as Free, and pure gift of Grace, in and through the Mediator. That they are one with the Father, through Chriſt. And the Love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Father Loveth Chriſt, is in them, becauſe Chriſt is in them. This never Ceaſes to Eternity, a dependence upon God in Chriſt a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104490:15"/>
            <p>I ſhall make but two brief Applications of what I have ſpoken, and ſo conclude. And,</p>
            <p>The Firſt Application I would make of it, is, To bring all our Hearts to that we read in the Goſpel, when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. 22. <hi>How often ſhall my Brother not ſin againſt me, and I forgive him? Till ſeven times? Jeſus ſaith unto him, I ſay unto thee, until ſeven times; but until ſeventy times ſeven.</hi> And in another Evangeliſt, when Chriſt had ſaid thus to <hi>Peter;</hi> He cries out in the great Senſe of this thing; It ſeemed ſo great a kind of Difficulty and Impoſſibility to him, the forgiving ſo often; Saith <hi>Peter,</hi> upon Chriſt's ſaying, there muſt be a forgiving ſo often; <hi>Lord, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this is that I deſire every one of us, to make uſe of what I have ſpoken to you; to cry out unto <hi>Chriſt, Lord, encreaſe our Faith.</hi> And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. 24. When the Father had brought his Children to Chriſt; and Chriſt told him, All things are poſſible to him that <hi>Believes;</hi> ſtraight-way the Father of the Child cryed out, and ſaid, with Tears, <hi>Lord, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, help mine unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I ſay, O that we could cry out with Tears! If Faith be ſuch a thing (as certainly it is; or this Book of God is not true) I ſay, certainly, Faith is ſuch a thing, as I have deſcribed. O that we could cry out with tears, in every caſe I have named to you! <hi>O Lord, I Believe; Help thou my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. That we could cry out with Tears!</hi> O! Want of Faith is the great want among us all. We have not ſo much Faith, as a <hi>Grain of Muſtard-Seed,</hi> certainly. O, How therefore are there not great things done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; becauſe we believe not! No great things done in our Souls; no great things done for us, in a way of Providence. There are no great and mighty Conqueſts over Luſts and Corruptions; No great and mighty Powers of Holineſs, and Heavenlineſs; becauſe we want Faith.</p>
            <p>Indeed, Men go to work without Faith; and they think they can ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the thing; But as I hope to have opportunity to ſhew you; No one in the World, can make ſo much as a <hi>grain of Muſtard ſeed;</hi> ſo not ſo much Faith as would amount to a <hi>grain of Muſtard ſeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! therefore, Let us cry out to Heaven for more Faith. We ſhould obtain Promiſes; we ſhould have great things done, if we had but more Faith. And then,</p>
            <p>The Second thing (with which I conclude) to beſeech you, to look to that Kingdom and Glory of Chriſt, wherein ſo much mighty Power, both of Faith and Action ſhall be given, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. 1. <hi>God is our Refuge and Strength, a very preſent help in trouble, therefore will we not fear, tho the Earth he removed,</hi> &amp;c. We ſhould not be ſo intimidated; ſo full of fear, if we had but Faith. Tho the <hi>Waters,</hi> &amp;c. even when <hi>Mountains were thrown in the midſt of the Sea, and the Waves Roaring; yet there ſhall be a ſtill, ſilent ſtream, that ſhall make glad the City of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3-4" type="sermons">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104490:15"/>
            <head>THE FAITH BY WHICH <hi>We are Iuſtified, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Third and Fourth Sermons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 5. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have, in the former Diſcourſes ſet out the Nature and Excellency of Faith, as it hath ſo cloſe an Union with, and derivation from Chriſt in the whole Nature and Action of it.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>I</hi> ſhall go on in ſhewing you how much All is in Chriſt, and not in Faith it ſelf, by ſhewing you; That if you conſider Faith as in it ſelf, it cannot be that which Juſtifies; if you conſider it, in, and by it ſelf. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Second Place, I ſhall more plainly lay down to you, how, and upon what account, Faith is ſaid to Juſtifie. And then,</p>
            <p>In the third Place, I ſhall ſhew you, that if <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf, <hi>conſidered</hi> in it ſelf, <hi>cannot Justify,</hi> Then the works of <hi>Faith,</hi> tho they be never ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, they <hi>cannot Juſtify,</hi> much leſs then faith it ſelf. And ſo <hi>conclude</hi> this point with the <hi>Application.</hi> And then, there will <hi>remain</hi> one point more <hi>concerning Faith,</hi> And that's the <hi>Plerophory</hi> and full <hi>Aſſurance. They have known ſurely that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> But that will be the laſt point.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104490:16"/>
            <p>The Firſt thing <hi>therefore</hi> that I ſhall <hi>endeavour</hi> (not in a <hi>Controverſal,</hi> but) in a <hi>Practical, Applicatory</hi> way, and in all the <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> of it, to all our hearts, in the <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>vertue of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt thing that I lay down, is this; that <hi>Faith conſidered</hi> as a work, It <hi>cannot Juſtify.</hi> The <hi>account</hi> that I give you of it is this; That <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> doth every where, when it ſpeaks <hi>preciſely</hi> and clearly to the point; It doth aſſure us, it is the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> And not the Faith that takes the Righteouſneſs of God.</p>
            <p>I deſire to be very far from <hi>ſtirring</hi> up any <hi>Controverſy;</hi> But to draw out our hearts (I ſay) into the <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Head</hi> 1. I begin now therefore to handle this great Point; and that is, Seeing we meet every where in Scripture, with theſe Expreſſions, <hi>Juſtified by Faith; The Righteouſneſs of Faith;</hi> The great Queſtion that I ſhall handle firſt, ſhall be to ſhew you, how, and in what ſenſe Faith <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies;</hi> and in what ſenſe it cannot be ſaid to <hi>juſtifie.</hi> For, indeed, this is a point very neceſſary to be cleared; ſeeing many are ready to ſay, That <hi>Faith</hi> is now inſtead of <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> and that it juſtifies, as the perfect Righteouſneſs of the Law ſhould have done; And that this is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition upon which Chriſt is ours, and upon which his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ours: and thus Faith Juſtifies. And thus Faith comes to be (through ſuch very Diſcourſes of Faith) an Eclipſe upon the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt. And ſo the Works of Faith come to be ſo alſo; for, ſay they, <hi>Every true, Faith muſt have VVorks.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>A Man is juſtified by VVorks, and not by Faith only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe things, they raiſe not only great Diſputes; concerning which it were indeed, much and earneſtly to be deſired, that they may be laid among the Servants of God; that they may be calmed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; becauſe it is greatly to the diſhonour of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that there ſhould be thoſe noiſes of Axes and Hammers in the Work of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and becauſe Men are ready to be ſcandalized; And it is <hi>told in Gath,</hi> and <hi>publiſhed in the ſtreets of Askalon,</hi> as the Expreſſion is. And therefore <hi>I</hi> ſay, we ſhould earneſtly deſire to ſpeak all the ſame thing, and to be in one Mind, and in one Judgment, according to the Truth of the Goſpel. And then, beſides, they are ready to ſtagger Souls, and to make them they know not which way to turn; and they muſt diſpute the things with themſelves; and ſo they are kept off from the healing that wound of Conſcience, and from the getting that <hi>full Aſſurance of Faith,</hi> and of <hi>Hope,</hi> and of <hi>Knowledge.</hi> So that while the wound of Conſcience, and the bleeding of Conſcience ſhould be ſtanched; and while the cloſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Blood of Chriſt ſhould work the Cure; the Souls and Spirits of Men are greatly in Diſpute and Perplexity, which way, and in what Method; what they ſhould lay firſt (as it were) to the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſcience, and to the diſtreſſed Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now, I have lately given you this Rule; and <hi>I</hi> would renew it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That you labour after, and ſeek after theſe things,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104490:16"/> from God; and that you would not perplex your ſelves about the term of Diſpute, in which theſe things are conveyed.</p>
            <p>O! Let but our Souls find that we have Chriſt indeed for ours, and that we apply to his Blood by <hi>Faith;</hi> and that we turn from every <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> by <hi>Repentance;</hi> and it is no matter for all the Diſputes about the Order, and whether a Man ſhould ſtay for this, or for that: But let him give up his Soul, according to the <hi>Impreſſion of Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet however, when we diſcourſe of theſe things plainly and peaceably, and according to the cleareſt Light and Reaſon of the Goſpel; they are to be attended to: And our Minds thereby, ſhall have <hi>Ideas</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations</hi> of them that may be ſuitable to the <hi>inward</hi> Caſe of our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>therefore,</hi> at this time, I ſhall lay down four <hi>Poſitions,</hi> in which, I ſhall open to you the nature of <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Relation</hi> to <hi>Juſtification:</hi> Or,</p>
            <p>The true nature of <hi>Justification,</hi> as it is taken in by <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt <hi>Poſition</hi> that I ſhall lay down, is this; I ſay, No <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but a <hi>Divine Righteouſneſs,</hi> an <hi>Everlaſting Righteouſneſs,</hi> can be the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of a Loſt and undone <hi>Sinner:</hi> Of an <hi>Immortal Eternal Soul,</hi> loſt and undone by ſin: No <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but a <hi>Divine Righteouſneſs;</hi> an <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Euerlasting Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! Keep this always in your mind: It muſt be ſuch a <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> Or it will not ſerve the great <hi>Purpoſe</hi> of your <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> thing that I would lay down, is this; that there is no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, that <hi>Faith,</hi> by any <hi>virtue,</hi> or <hi>Excellency</hi> of its own, ſhould be our <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, tho there be a great <hi>Renown</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Graces of the <hi>Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God, and the working of that <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in the Hearts and Lives of <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtians;</hi> yet ſtill, it is not with <hi>Relation</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> ſo as to be our <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> But onely (as I ſhall ſhew you) it takes in the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and wherein the <hi>Excellency</hi> of it lyes, to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third</hi> place; the <hi>Third Poſition</hi> that I would lay down, is this;</p>
            <p>That tho it is true, that the <hi>Faith</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſpeaks of, is a vigorous, working, active <hi>Faith;</hi> yet, the works of <hi>Faith</hi> are further off from the Juſtifying of a <hi>Sinner,</hi> than <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf is.</p>
            <p>So, that take the moſt <hi>excellent</hi> works of any of the Believers in <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> It is not their works: I ſay it is not their works that are their <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to <hi>Juſtification;</hi> they are further off from <hi>Juſtification,</hi> than their <hi>Faith</hi> is: And yet this <hi>Faith</hi> cannot be their <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Poſition</hi> that I would lay down, is this; that <hi>Faith</hi> has not a <hi>Power</hi> of it ſelf, to take <hi>Chriſt:</hi> But <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gives himſelf to the <hi>Soul:</hi> And then the <hi>mighty Power</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> flows out from him, and <hi>Twines</hi> about <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and unites it ſelf unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104490:17"/>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Four Poſitions,</hi> I do not find, upon the moſt ſevere <hi>Examination,</hi> that they do in the leaſt <hi>Abridge,</hi> or take off any thing from the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and from the duties in which all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are to be found. And yet, they give us indeed, the truth of the freeneſs of the Grace of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and will Redeem us from all miſtakes and <hi>miſapprehenſions,</hi> or from leſſening the <hi>Glory of Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Begin at this time with the Firſt of them: And that is, that no <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but an <hi>Everlaſting, a Divine Righteouſneſs</hi> can poſſibly ſerve the caſe of our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You find therefore in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24. <hi>When Jeſus Chriſt came into his great Action, as a Mediator; He is ſaid to finiſh tranſgreſſion, and to make an end of ſin, and to make Reconciliation for Iniquity, and to bring in Everlasting Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> He brings in <hi>Everlaſting Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> has an Expreſſion; which I confeſs, one would be ready (If one does not weigh, and compare it with the whole <hi>Scripture</hi>) to think, it was the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of Holy works onely, he, or rather the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> intended by him in it. But if we conſider it cloſe, and with the whole <hi>Scripture;</hi> there is Reaſon to look upon it, as having Relation to the great ſalvation, by the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt. Pſal.</hi> 119. 144 <hi>The Righteouſneſs of thy Teſtimonies is Everlaſting,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſay, it does ſeem to refer to thoſe <hi>Righteous</hi> and <hi>Holy Precepts</hi> of God. But, he calls it, the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of thy <hi>Teſtimonies;</hi> That is, the Great <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Revelation</hi> that God hath given anew, by the word. Not that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> that was <hi>written</hi> upon the heart of man; But the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Testimony</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of God. And therefore, give me <hi>underſtanding</hi> herein, and I ſhall live. According as he ſaid, there is a <hi>Covenant</hi> made with me <hi>ordered in all things, and ſure.</hi> And, it is an <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of his <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> is to be expounded by thoſe very words, <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23. 5. <hi>Although my houſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And though his houſe was not ſo with God: That is, though he could not come up any way, either before <hi>Converſion,</hi> or after <hi>Converſion,</hi> to the <hi>Holineſs</hi> that every perſon is tyed by to the <hi>Law:</hi> Yet there is an <hi>Everlaſting Covenant ordered in all things, and ſure, Which is all our ſalvation and all our hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening therefore of this Poſition, to you more fully; The <hi>Firſt</hi> thing that I deſire may be well <hi>Apprehended</hi> by us, is this;</p>
            <p>That there is no <hi>Communication</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God himſelf: I ſay, of God himſelf, through the humane nature of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> The <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of him, who is <hi>Eternal God,</hi> through the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature;</hi> No other <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> is that <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> that the <hi>Goſpel Expreſſes</hi> to us for <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, you know, it is ſeveral times in <hi>Scripture,</hi> called the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God. Indeed the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are not to be numbred Eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thoſe in the <hi>New Testament</hi> call it the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God. I know,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104490:17"/> It may be Interpreted to be called the Righteouſneſs of God; becauſe it is a Righteouſneſs of God's providing, and that he approves. But there is one place of <hi>Scripture</hi> that will clear this to us, that there is more intended than that, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8, 9. <hi>Saith the Apoſtle, yea doubtleſs I count all but Droſs that I may be found in Chriſt, not having my own Righteouſneſs, but that which is of God, the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith of Jeſus Christ.</hi> Obſerve the Righteouſneſs of the Law is truly the Righteouſneſs of God, ſo far as it is Commanded, and ſo far as any one can have it; that is, the Righteouſneſs that God hath Commanded, and that God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. But that which is by the Faith of Chriſt, is the Righteouſneſs which is of God, which flows from God, and is received by Faith; the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith.</p>
            <p>The great Fountain of it is God himſelf in Jeſus. And therefore there is nothing ſo great in Scripture, as the Apprehending of Chriſt the Son of God, by Faith. You ſhall find oftentimes, he is ſo called, <hi>The Son of God.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 17. 7, 8. <hi>They have known that I came out from thee, and that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> Here is this very thing, our Lord intends, to ſhew himſelf that Divine Perſon, that is, <hi>The Son of God, John</hi> 9. Conſider that place; that you may know how to direct and place your Faith. You muſt not reſt in the Humanity of Chriſt, in the Man Chriſt Jeſus; But your Reſt muſt be in the Divinty of Chriſt; the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt. There's the great <hi>Rock</hi> (as Chriſt told <hi>Peter</hi>) that the <hi>Church is founded upon.</hi> As the <hi>living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; therefore, I beſeech you, that we may all go to the very height of this: That is, to look to Jeſus Chriſt, as the Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 9. 33. They caſt out the blind Man, that Jeſus had healed; They caſt him out of the Synagogue: When Chriſt found him, he ſaid unto him, <hi>Do'ſt thou believe on the Son of God?</hi> Pray obſerve, <hi>Do'ſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on the Son of God?</hi> He did not ſay, Do'ſt thou believe on me, that thou ſeeſt before thee, in the Figure and appearance of a Man, and to be truly a Man? But <hi>do'ſt thou believe on the Son of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, there may be places of Scripture, where Chriſt ſpeaks of Believing in himſelf, without this high Stile: But when there is one great place of Scripture, or ſeveral great places (I may rather ſay) that lead higher; It is certainly our Duty to go up to the higheſt, and to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all thither. Now (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>do'ſt thou believe on the Son of God?</hi> He Anſwered, and ſaid, <hi>Who is he, Lord, that I might believe in him?</hi> And <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto him, thou haſt both ſeen him, and it is he that talketh with thee.</hi> And he ſaid, <hi>Lord, I believe, and he worſhipped him.</hi> Here is the excellent Order of Faith, we muſt go up to the height; <hi>To the Son of God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then conſider the Communication; through the Human Nature; <hi>I am he,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Thou haſt ſeen him; and it is he that talketh with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'll give you one very Evident place of Scripture more to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; that your Faith and your Hope might be in the Son of God. O!
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104490:18"/> could we but apprehend the Righteouſneſs of the Son of God to be our Righteouſneſs; what a Rock of Support and Defence would it be to our Souls? How would it ſatisfy our Scruples, and all our Fears? Indeed, it is a high act of Faith, to lay hold thus upon the Son of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt was <hi>Crucified through weakneſs,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. <hi>He was Crucified through weakneſs:</hi> That is, as a man: <hi>But he lives by the Power of God:</hi> That is, by the Divinity. Now (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>I am Crucified with Chriſt:</hi> I receive by Communication from Jeſus Chriſt, as Man, a Crucifixion of my own Righteouſneſs; <hi>So the Life which I live in the Fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God,</hi> &amp;c. who hath conveyed his Salvation, through his Human Nature. The great height of Faith, is to reach Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God. So in 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. You may ſee how the Divine Excellency of Chriſt ſtreams through his Human Nature, unto eternal Life. <hi>That which was from the begining.</hi> He does not ſay, He that was from the begining; <hi>But that which was from the begining,</hi> to direct our Hearts more Emphatically to the Eternal Word, which we have heard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Speaking of Jeſus Chriſt, eſpecially and principally of his Divine Nature: And yet Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated through Human Nature. So that we have <hi>ſeen with our Eyes, and looked upon; and our hands have handled the word of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore is the firſt thing, that we may underſtand the Nature of Juſtification; It is the Righteouſneſs of the Son of God, conveyed through the Human Nature.</p>
            <p>In the Second place, which I have mentioned in general Phraſes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; and I would now imprint upon all our Hearts, through the Grace of God. That is, it is not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt divided from himſelf; but the perſon of Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs of Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from Chriſt; but the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in himſelf, as that perſon from whom it always flows. So, that our Faith, it muſt be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt. For, indeed, this is a great miſtake in our underſtanding, and in the working of our Hearts to Chriſt, tho <hi>I</hi> would not entangle any Perſon, in the nicities of Diſcourſe; But, by touching, and apprehending, and applying the Benefits of Chriſt, the Believer does really take Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>Yet, that we may clearlier underſtand this thing; <hi>I</hi> ſay, it is not a Righteouſneſs cut off from Chriſt, and imputed to us: As if Chriſt ſhould ſay, Here <hi>I</hi> lay you down ſo much Righteouſneſs; a Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that <hi>I</hi> am ſure, will Anſwer, in every regard, for you: And take that Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>As if a Man ſhould lay down a great Treaſure of Gold, to a poor man, or to a man in neceſſity; a Man in Diſtreſs; and ſhould ſay, <hi>I</hi> lay you down this Gold; this ſhall Anſwer every thing, that preſſes upon you;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104490:18"/> and ſo he goes away, and leaves the Gold; and the perſon Apprehends, and applies the Gold to his uſe: But he has but a far off-conſideration of the perſon.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>I</hi> ſay, this is not fully our Caſe. Tho <hi>I</hi> would not be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing to any Soul; and eſpecially, a Diſtreſſed and Tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; as if he muſt find out theſe Nicities of Notion in his own Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or he cannot be Chriſts: But (<hi>I</hi> ſay) as the perſon that ſhould receive this Gold; he may be united in his Affection, and Love, and in his Truſt, and Dependence, to ſuch a perſon, tho his notions of him are but dark; but here the true Righteouſneſs is always going out from Chriſt, as the Light is from the Sun. And, as the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, he gives out this Righteouſneſs, ſo from himſelf, that it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver parts from himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is not a thing by it ſelf; that Chriſt is one thing, and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is another: But, by taking the Perſon of Chriſt, and by our being United to him; we come thereby, to have the ſtream of his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and the Beams of it continually Flowing out, and ſhining upon us. And therefore this is the thing that we are to look to; O! that our Hearts might be made Wiſe in it; and might be enabled to it, to take the Son of God himſelf. As, indeed, it has been the Doctrine of the Antient Servants of Chriſt, who were called, in their time, the <hi>Puritan Preachers:</hi> This Doctrine hath been delivered long ago, very excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> particularly, a Man of great Name, in the ſervice of the Goſpel; this is the thing we muſt look to; To have the perſon of Chriſt for ours; we muſt be United to him, as the great Redeemer; And ſo his Righteouſneſs flows out. That it is a Compariſon we all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand he makes great uſe of. As a poor Woman, ſuppoſe, cloathed mean; and a diſtreſſed perſon: And a great perſon is pleaſed to take her, and Eſpouſe her to him. It is not all the Riches, and Eſtate that ſuch a perſon hath, that ſhould pleaſe ſuch an eſpouſed Perſon; But it muſt be the very perſon that is pleaſed to eſpouſe her; that muſt be the Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Soul to Unite to him.</p>
            <p>And ſo Jeſus Chriſt muſt be the endeared one of our Souls. <hi>My belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is mine, and I am his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, in that of <hi>Malachi,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> was naming to you; it does very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably make out the thing, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>But unto you that fear my Name, the Son of Righteouſneſs ſhall riſe with healing in his Wings.</hi> You know, the Sun, it does not part with its Beams, and with its Rays, tho it gives us their Light; but it keeps them entirely within it ſelf: So that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not clip off a Beam, by all the Art in the World, from the Sun, and ſay, Here <hi>I</hi> have clipt off a Beam from the Sun, and I'll keep it; it ſhall ſerve me for light, by Night and Day; You know, this is impoſſible: he muſt have the very preſence of the Sun, or he cannot have the Beams and the Rays of the Sun.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104490:19"/>
            <p>So we cannot have the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, but by having the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for ours. And, ſaith he, <hi>the healing is in his wings;</hi> it is always in his Wings. Indeed, the vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of it paſſes from the Wing, unto the Souls of the People. But, if you could part betwixt the Sun and the healing, or the Wings and the Healings; the healing Power would preſently be gone, and loſt. Therefore I ſay, it is our great buſineſs to keep cloſe to Chriſt; As I ſhall urge further ſtill, in the proſecution of this Point. But you ſee how the Scripture runs every where upon this. <hi>Who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> And, <hi>found in Chriſt.</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>Who of God is made Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You have not Wiſdom by it ſelf; and Righteouſnrſs by it ſelf; and Sanctification and Glory by it ſelf; But you have them all, by having Chriſt: <hi>Of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> There is nothing ſo clear as this thing, that I am now upon, in Scripture: I ſay, nothing ſo clear; and ſo in 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life,</hi> &amp;c. Here is the Caſe: it is not Righteouſneſs by it ſelf: <hi>But he that hath the Son hath Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I would but deſire, as I hope here are many at this time, that can underſtand in good meaſure: I know, the thing is beyond all our Underſtanding, as to the perfection of it: But in good meaſure, I hope we may underſtand. And I would deſire you but to conſider, that if this point were but truly taken in; how preſently it would make an end of all that Controverſy concerning Juſtification. For, if we are but fully poſſeſt, that this Righteouſneſs flows only from Chriſt; Chriſt in his Perſon, what room for Diſpute, what our Righteouſneſs to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is.</p>
            <p>I'll give you but one Scripture, and ſo paſs off from this Head, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25. Wherein the Spirit of God makes uſe of this Similitude I named to you, out of Dr. <hi>Preſton:</hi> That is, of an Union; a Marriage Union. <hi>Husbands love your Wives:</hi> From 25th <hi>ver.</hi> to the 32. <hi>For we are members of his Body; of his Fleſh, and of his Bones.</hi> If it were not ſo, his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could be no more our Righteouſneſs, than (as the Papiſts ſpeak) the whiteneſs and Beauty of another perſon, could be our Beauty, or Whiteneſs, or our pure Complexion. And ſo it would be, if we were not Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones. <hi>And for this cauſe, ſhall a man leave his father and mother, and ſhall be joyned to his wife. This is a Great myſtery,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: But yet I <hi>ſpeak concerning Chriſt, and his Church.</hi> That is, there is a true Marriage Union: All other Marriage Union is but a Foil, to ſet off the Greatneſs of that Marriage Union betwixt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his Church. That is, All the <hi>Souls</hi> of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Communion,</hi> and <hi>Communication.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third Place;</hi> To bring this thing to a Head. The truth is, <hi>Righteouſneſs to Justification</hi> is in <hi>Chriſt</hi> only: And that's the ſum of all that can be ſaid. For, if we be united to Chriſt; It is no <hi>Improper</hi> thing, that we ſhould have his Righteouſneſs for ours.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104490:19"/>
            <p>You know, that marriage, it conveys a Right to the wife, of all that the husband hath: So <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a ſupremacy of Righteouſneſs, of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> but ſtill, he gives a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> And the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may well be our <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> If we are <hi>members</hi> of his <hi>Body;</hi> of his fleſh, and of his bones. As you know, the Head, and all parts, they ſhare one with another; in either the Honour, the Glory; the Acquittal, or in the <hi>Condemnation</hi> of any one particular. Therefore the <hi>Fourth Particular</hi> is this;</p>
            <p>That indeed, if any one could frame a <hi>Notion</hi> of the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> to be his <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> Or, of the Blood and Death of Chriſt to be his, for Juſtification, and Pardon, and clearing from ſin; If that Righteouſneſs ſeparated from Chriſt; It would be no other to us, and in us, but as a <hi>Creature-Righteouſneſs,</hi> and as a <hi>ſelf-Righteouſneſs:</hi> And for us to truſt in it, and to ſtay our ſelves upon it; would be a truſting to our own <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, as it is in him, a <hi>Spring,</hi> and a <hi>Fountain;</hi> There is the Life, and there is the Glory of it.</p>
            <p>I'll give you but one <hi>Scripture, Rom.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Mark, Here's a Receiving abundance of Grace, and of the gift of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Nothing can be more expreſs than this; A man takes in by Faith <hi>abundance of Grace,</hi> and <hi>of the gift of Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, the Queſtion is, does he live by this <hi>receiving abundance of Grace,</hi> and of <hi>the Gift of Righteouſneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: For, the Apoſtle goes on; <hi>He ſhall reign in Life by one Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He ſhall not reign by abundance of Grace, and of the gift of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which he receives ſimply, and ſeparately, and diſtinct from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> But he ſhall reign in life by one <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, this <hi>Scripture</hi> does cut off all diſputes, and all Controverſies; and ſhews, that Juſtification is onely by union to Chriſt, and by nothing elſe, whatſover is the abundance of Grace, and of the Gift of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; And healed by the Wings of Chriſt, and flowing out, and Righteouſneſs ſtreaming out continually, from the Sun of it; that is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Oh then that we were but clear in this great truth of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, <hi>Jehovah being our Righteouſneſs.</hi> For, if ſuch a poor weak thing, as Faith, becauſe it is conformable (as is ſuppoſed) to the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Law,</hi> were our Righteouſneſs, we ſhould have Reaſon to fear, and much more, becauſe indeed, no one comes up ſo much as to the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Law,</hi> as they would phraſe it: Our Faith is ſo weak and low, that if we were to be Juſtified by it, we ſhould be utterly undone, even by that which we call the <hi>Goſpel-Law,</hi> but when it does, but onely attend the Communication and giving of the Righteouſneſs of the <hi>Eternal Jehovab</hi> to us; when it does onely that; O we that are in this Righteouſneſs, and are made the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> It is impoſſible we ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104490:20"/> be condemned: We muſt needs <hi>condemn every tongue,</hi> that <hi>riſes in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us,</hi> becauſe we have the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jehovah.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the thing is ſo great; that many even would be ready to look upon it, as ſtrange, and next to <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi> But it is the very words of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and even the thing it ſelf it always preſſes; Not that we are Righteous, as God is Righteous, (As ſome would Infer from ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions) or Righteous as Chriſt is Righteous: That is, according to the Divine Original Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> or according to any perfections that are proper to him: But that we are utterly uncondem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and ſet out of the reach of <hi>Condemnation</hi> hereby; and arrayed, as in our degree, with this rich <hi>Robe;</hi> Becauſe it is the Righteouſneſs of God we are found in; and that we are made by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to Chriſt,</hi> the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God. And yet all the diſtinction that ought to be preſerved to the greatneſs of the Righteouſneſs of God, and Chriſt, is ſtill preſerved.</p>
            <p>And that's the firſt thing, in which I would open this point.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is to ſhew you, that Faith in it ſelf, it cannot be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as our Righteouſneſs; Becauſe there is a great deal of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in all our <hi>Reaſon and Apprehenſion,</hi> between the taking of a Gift, and the Gift. Becauſe I take a great Gift; ſhall therefore my taking be counted of Equal value with the Gift? You know this is contrary to all our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to all our <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> in the caſe. A man may have a <hi>Pearl</hi> of <hi>Incomparable</hi> value given to him, ſuppoſe in a ſtate of <hi>neceſſity</hi> and want: Shall his taking of the Gift, or of the <hi>Pearl</hi> be look'd upon, as of equal value, with the <hi>Pearl</hi> it ſelf? Why now, if we were Juſtified by Faith, as it is a work, or an act of ours, or any thing, let it be called by what name it will; as it is in us; would it therefore Juſtify us, as it is in us? Becauſe of its taking of an <hi>incomparable, invaluable gift;</hi> muſt it be equal with the gift it ſelf?</p>
            <p>Therefore, though <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks ſo much of <hi>Faith</hi> as it does; and of being Juſtified by Faith; yet, let Faith lye low before Chriſt. For, It is not our taking, If it were the moſt perfect act, it could be ſuppoſed; But it is not ſo: But we have Reaſon to cry out, <hi>Lord, I believe; help thou mine unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it were ſo; It were nothing at all in the caſe. As you know, the moſt perfect, and grateful, and delightful Receiving of a gift, can no way anſwer or ſtand in account with the gift it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, this I deſire ſhould be Imprinted upon our ſpirits; both to take down all imagination of our ſelves; and alſo to give Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, in many of the Anguiſhes, and Agonies of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that come upon Believers through the weakneſs of their Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>They which receive</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>abundance of Grace.</hi> Now, can any of us ſuppoſe, that the Receiving abundance of Grace ſhould be any way equal to the abundance of Grace it ſelf?</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104490:20"/>
            <p>And ſo, in the firſt Chapter of <hi>John;</hi> ſaith the Evangeliſt there; <hi>He came unto his own;</hi> and his <hi>own received him not. But to as many as receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ver.</hi> 12. Now I would deſire to ask you, whether you think, that the receiving of him, (that is, of Chriſt) whether it be any way matchable, or can countervail the Excellency of Chriſt himſelf? Or whether it can come near, in any of the vertues, or the Powers of Jeſus Chriſt, to Adoption, or Juſtification? therefore it is moſt evidently cleared, that it is not the worth of Faith, or the Excellency of Faith, or the Activity, or Applicatorineſs of Faith: But it is wholly in that Great, and Excellent, and Infinite Perſon, whom we receive by Faith; there's the whole of the thing.</p>
            <p>And therefore, If you ask, where is our Riches, where's our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, where's our Strength?</p>
            <p>It is evident, it is not in our receiving; But in him whom we receive. It is not in our receiving; but in the abundance of Grace, and of the Gift of Righteouſneſs, that we receive, together with the receiving of Chriſt himſelf; and no otherwiſe. Not by receiving of it, and going away with it from Chriſt, and ſaying, we have it now: But by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe to him, as our <hi>Sun,</hi> and as our <hi>Fountain;</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and <hi>Fountain</hi> of Righteouſneſs; keeping cloſe to him: And ſo that Righteouſneſs of his, overflows, and runs out, upon us; and then, as I ſaid, our Conſolation depends upon it. For, O! How do we find our hand to ſhake?</p>
            <p>A Paralytick hand, a Palſy hand it is that the beſt of us have. And if we depend upon that, the hold that we take; certainly, this Rich Righteouſneſs; this <hi>Incomparable Rich Pearl</hi> will fall out of our hand. Do but conſider how our hand ſhakes in all our layings hold on Chriſt. But indeed it is the Jewel it ſelf that will be ours; that is pleaſed to be ours. That is, Jeſus Chriſt is pleaſed to be ours, and though our hand ſhakes in the taking of him; yet it cannot ſhake, or Palſy (as I may ſo expreſs) the love of Chriſt, in giving himſelf: He is conſtant and Invariable in that. Where he loves a Soul, he loves him to the End. As it is ſaid peculiarly of Chriſt, in that of <hi>John;</hi> when he was about to dye; being about to depart out of the world, <hi>having loved his own, which were in the world, he loved them to the end. Chap.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
            <p>Now if you conſider how they behave themſelves, Pray do but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; I ſay, how theſe <hi>Own</hi> behaved themſelves, at that time, when he was going out of the world: They left him; they fled from him; they forſook him: And <hi>Peter</hi> that pretended higheſt, denyed him moſt ſhamefully.</p>
            <p>Now, I ſay, if it had depended upon their Faith; they had certainly loſt Chriſt. But having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end: So, though our Faith is never ſo weak, never ſo imperfect; yet he that hath ſaid, I have given my ſelf for them, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104490:21"/> loved them; He holds them faſt to his own Gift, and within his own Gift: though they would ten thouſand times, (as I may ſo expreſs it) let him go, if it depended upon their Faith.</p>
            <p>Now in all theſe things, I humbly deſire to call God to witneſs, that I do not ſpeak for expreſſion-ſake, or to ſet out a thing with all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage I can; But really, as <hi>Scripture</hi> gives evidence, and as I hope, I am perſwaded of the truth of the thing in my own heart, by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Divine</hi> ſpirit. Neither to manage a Controverſy, or any thing of that; But that it is the neceſſity of our Caſe, that it ſhould be thus; Or elſe we are loſt and undone, though never ſo much were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to Faith; Becauſe our Faith is ſuch a Cripple, ſuch a Lame hand, and foot in taking Chriſt, and coming to him; that we ſhould certainly loſe him, if he did not reſolve to make good his own Gift of himſelf to us. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Third Place; <hi>I</hi> argue, that it cannot be in Faith it ſelf; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then Chriſt ſhould dye to bring in ſomething more imperfect, than the firſt Righteouſneſs that was given to man. Chriſt ſhould dye to bring in ſomething more imperfect; and yet ſtill it ſhould be our own, and we ſhould glory in it, even as our firſt Righteouſneſs. For now, when God made man; he made him perfect (as the <hi>Scripture</hi> expreſſes) he made him in his own image, in his own Righteouſneſs, knowledge, and in true holineſs. And there was a Perfection; there was no blem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, as to the Creation of God, and ſo far as it could be in a Creature. Why now, God, in his infinite wiſdom, in the <hi>Abyſs</hi> and unfathoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble depth of his own wiſdom and underſtanding; He leaves man to fall; And all men, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> argues, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. They have ſinned, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſhort of the Glory of God. And what is it that follows from this?</p>
            <p>It therefore follows (ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) that there can be no <hi>Glorying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,</hi> ver. 27. <hi>Where is boaſting then? It is Excluded: By what Law? Of works?</hi> No; <hi>But by the Law of Faith, Boaſting is Excluded.</hi> Now <hi>I</hi> ſay, if works that were perfect, were excluded, becauſe they would be looked upon as our own merit; and Faith is brought in; and if that ſhould be brought in, as our own; and that ſhould Juſtify us, as our own Faith: Why then it would be a more imperfect thing than the firſt Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>For, take Faith as it is in us; it is more imperfect than the firſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs, in which God created man; and yet it ſhould be our own; and boaſting ſhould ariſe from this, that we have believed. Nay, if it were our believing; then it were a more imperfect thing, <hi>I</hi> ſay, that is brought in; and boaſting would not be excluded by this Law of Faith. And therefore it is very evident, that Faith is not the thing that Juſtifveth; but onely that which Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth; that is, the Righteouſneſs of God in Jeſus Chriſt, is the onely
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104490:21"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing that Juſtifieth. And this I deſire ſhould be imprinted upon our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>houghts, upon our hearts, to this great end and purpoſe, that we may always lye low before God; and that we may ſay, we will boaſt in him all the day long, Living and Dying; and were we but able to be cut off from every thing in our ſelves, and to lay faſt hold upon God and Chriſt; and to have our whole in him; our whole in God, our whole in Chriſt; This is the true life of Faith, the true Excellency of Faith, to have nothing at all in all in ourſelves; as I ſhall ſpeak further to you.</p>
            <p>Therefore I go on to the Fourth Particular; And that is to affirm this, <hi>That it cannot be by Faith, as any thing of it ſelf; becauſe the Righteouſneſs of the Law, that was given man in his Creation, was as free a Gift as Faith it ſelf is now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any one ſhould ſay, But herein is a difference; The Work of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in the firſt Creation, and the Habits of it, they were our own; But Faith is a free gift.</p>
            <p>I ſay, There is no difference in this; for Faith is no more a free gift, than the Righteouſneſs that <hi>Adam</hi> had at firſt was a free gift.</p>
            <p>In confeſs indeed, there was a becomingneſs, that the Creator ſhould make his Work perfect: But it was <hi>Grace, free Grace,</hi> that gave to Man at firſt his Being, and that gave to Man all the Accompliſhments of his Being. And therefore there is not ſo great difference in that.</p>
            <p>But herein is the great difference, That now all that we have is in God, and by him, and from him alone; and it is never ſeparated from him. I look upon this to be the great difference between <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt Eſtate, and in the Creation of Angels; and a ſinner now in Chriſt, reconciled to God; that we have all in Chriſt, and never out of him; whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we had all in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhould ſay, I'll take the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and ſay, Here I'll take my Portion; it is given in; and it is out of God, and out of Chriſt; it is in me: This would preſently be a broken Ciſtern, or it would dry up of it ſelf; it would fail, or let out that precious thing committed to it. It would certainly do ſo; and therefore here's our great ſecurity, that we are never out of God and Chriſt, as is evident (throughout Eternity) by the 17<hi>th</hi> of <hi>John:</hi> That they all may be one, <hi>As thou, Father, art in me, that they alſo may be one in us. And the glory which thou haſt given me, I have given them,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo Chriſt is even in them; and his Righteouſneſs, and his Glory, and his Perfection, are always in himſelf, and in a Communication unto them, and they in Union with him, and in that Communication.</p>
            <p>If this be not truly the ſenſe, and the Spirit of the Goſpel, I muſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, I am not in any capacity to ſpeak of theſe things. For there is nothing more evident to me than this, <hi>That our whole Salvation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Goſpel, does no more ſtir out of God and Chriſt, than</hi> (to ſpeak of a thing that we know) <hi>we ſee now the Beams of the Sun, and the Light of the Sun</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104490:22"/> 
               <hi>ſtir out of the Sun, but all is in the Sun.</hi> For, if any one ſhould go to ſay, this Room or Place is full of Light, or full of the Beams of the <hi>Sun;</hi> we'll preſently ſhut up all the Avenues between us and the <hi>Sun;</hi> and we'll have the Light as our own; you know how preſently the place would be dark, and there would be no remainder of Light at all in it, becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> is ſhut out.</p>
            <p>So now, and to <hi>Eternity;</hi> if you could ſhut out God and <hi>Christ,</hi> the Eternal fountain of Righteouſneſs from any Soul; that Soul would be immediately dark as to the ſtate of Grace; and ſo grow darker and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the darkneſs of Hell. And now, in the fifth Place,</p>
            <p>If the Righteouſneſs of Faith were a Righteouſneſs onely becauſe it is freely given; why then, Love and Repentance, and Obedience, they are all freely given, even as Faith: And yet for all this, <hi>Scripture</hi> never ſpeaks of them as Juſtifying.</p>
            <p>And therefore I come to the laſt thing, to ſhew you wherein Faith Juſtifies; It is onely in this; that by the moſt ſimple and abſtracted, and the moſt naked <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> of the thing that can be; It has nothing, but what it is made to receive, in this great point of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> I ſay, it is made to receive, and to do nothing but to receive: It is made to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and to do <hi>nothing</hi> but to depend; To truſt, and to do nothing but truſt.</p>
            <p>I do <hi>acknowledge,</hi> there's a great vertue of <hi>Faith outward;</hi> but this is that <hi>Immanent</hi> act of <hi>Faith</hi> (As I may ſo ſpeak) as <hi>Divines</hi> call thoſe <hi>Immanent</hi> acts of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that do not go out of <hi>Himſelf.</hi> So I ſay, that <hi>Immanent</hi> act of <hi>Faith</hi> that is <hi>betwixt</hi> Chriſt and the <hi>Soul:</hi> It is to truſt, and onely to truſt; to <hi>depend,</hi> and onely to <hi>depend;</hi> and to <hi>receive,</hi> and onely to <hi>receive.</hi> And, as for <hi>Faith;</hi> It hath <hi>nothing,</hi> It is <hi>nothing,</hi> but onely this <hi>Receipt.</hi> So it is the moſt perfect <hi>dependence</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> hath upon <hi>Chriſt. I will truſt, and not be afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12. 2. And in that day thou ſhalt ſay, <hi>O Lord, I will praiſe thee: though thou waſt angry with me, thine anger is turned away, and thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteſt me.</hi> Behold, God is my <hi>Salvation:</hi> I will truſt, and not be afraid.</p>
            <p>Here therefore is the great <hi>Excellency</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> the meet <hi>Excellency</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> not in it ſelf; but onely that it wholly depends; It is made, and fitted by God, on <hi>purpoſe</hi> wholly to depend.</p>
            <p>I would come now to the ſecond thing that I propoſed; which I ſhall very briefly repreſent to you.</p>
            <p>For, if <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf can do nothing; It is certain then, that the works of <hi>Faith</hi> can do nothing.</p>
            <p>And therefore that great objection that is made againſt this, out of the 2d of <hi>James:</hi> that <hi>Faith which hath not works is Dead, and can't Juſtify.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is nothing at all to this Great Point: But onely this it is indeed; to ſhew us, that if any man has <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> this <hi>Faith</hi> ſhall appear not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104490:22"/> to be an Idle, and a <hi>Dead Faith;</hi> But it ſhall every way be active, from the <hi>Power</hi> it receiveth from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to walk in all ways of <hi>obedience:</hi> to Render up the <hi>Soul</hi> entirely, in the Love of God (<hi>according</hi> to the preſent ſtate, I mean) with <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>uprightneſs.</hi> But it is not to this great point. For, it is very plain, when two things are ſpoken of in <hi>Scripture;</hi> If there be a higher, and a Lower; the Lower muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſubordinated to the higher; that, I look upon to be a ſtable and <hi>unchangeable Rule.</hi> Now we are ſaid to be <hi>Juſtified</hi> by a <hi>Faith</hi> that is not without works, and yet without works we are <hi>Juſtified;</hi> and in other places we are ſaid to be <hi>Juſtified</hi> in God. <hi>In the Lord ſhall all the ſeed of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>be Justified, and ſhall Glory.</hi> And <hi>Jehovah is our Righteouſneſs;</hi> And the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Now I ſay, that which is infinitely above <hi>Faith;</hi> As we will all grant; God, and the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, Chriſt, and the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are far above <hi>Faith.</hi> Why then, though ſometimes we are ſaid to be <hi>Justified</hi> by <hi>Faith;</hi> and the <hi>Faith</hi> by which we are <hi>Juſtified,</hi> is ſaid to have works. Yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the, <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> muſt infinitely take place of theſe; becauſe they are ſo far above, in the <hi>Tranſcendency</hi> and Infiniteneſs of their own nature. So that it can never be, that the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, and of Chriſt can be brought down. Therefore we are ſaid ſometimes to be <hi>Juſtified</hi> by <hi>Faith;</hi> But it is very plain, that Faith, in its <hi>Juſtifying</hi> Power, it muſt be brought up to God and Chriſt. And there is all that is to be ſaid of it; that it takes hold of God, and Chriſt. That's the whole of it; it takes hold of God, and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore indeed, I cannot but think of that expreſſion; though I don't ſay, it will hold in this. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays the <hi>Spider</hi> is <hi>very wiſe,</hi> becauſe it takes hold with its hands; and <hi>is in Kings Palaces.</hi> The Spider ſeems a baſe Creature: yet notwithſtanding the baſeneſs and poiſonouſneſs of its nature; yet in this, it prefers and advances it ſelf; becauſe it <hi>takes hold with its hands</hi> and <hi>is in Kings Palaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I ſay, in regard of us, who are poiſoned with ſin and Corruption; yet Faith takes <hi>hold with its hand;</hi> and it is in the Righteouſneſs of God, and in the Righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt. Now ſtill, if you look upon us in our ſelves; or look upon Faith in it ſelf; Alas! What can it do? onely it can take hold of the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> and the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Jeſus Chriſt. And therefore I do acknowledge, that Faith is of great power and vertue. The 11 <hi>Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> makes evident, as well as the 2d of <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I wonder, that men look ſo diſproportionably: The great things there aſcribed to Faith all along, in the 11<hi>th</hi> of <hi>Heb.</hi> make out the very ſame thing; So that the <hi>Apoſtle James</hi> did not contradict the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> nor the <hi>Apostle Paul</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle James,</hi> both of them ſpeaking by the ſpirit of <hi>God;</hi> and therefore I ſay, Faith indeed is of great Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of great operation, but it takes hold of Chriſt onely by way of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104490:23"/> Receipt and dependence; and ſo we are alone Juſtified by it. <hi>I</hi> would fain clear one particular more; that you may be very abſolute in this great point, wherein the Excellency of Faith lyes. And that is,</p>
            <p>You may ſay ſtill; why, Faith is a great thing indeed: And ſo far as it is ours, we may look upon it as a great thing; if it can take hold of <hi>God,</hi> and of Chriſt, and of the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> and of Jeſus Chriſt. What is like it in the whole world, if it can do this?</p>
            <p>Therefore, though <hi>I</hi> acknowledge all that <hi>Scripture</hi> hath ſpoken by way of Commendation of Faith; yet <hi>I</hi> muſt humble Faith (as <hi>I</hi> may ſo expreſs it) before you, as to this very particular. For, Faith could no more take <hi>God,</hi> or Chriſt; or the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> or of Chriſt; than any of us can ſpan the whole Heaven, or take the whole Heaven into our hands. It is nothing but onely this wherein Faith excels, that <hi>God,</hi> and Chriſt give themſelves, with infinite Riches of <hi>Grace.</hi> And Chriſt gives himſelf; he gives himſelf to Faith.</p>
            <p>This is that, that <hi>I</hi> poſitively affirm; that Faith has no more Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to take hold of <hi>God,</hi> and Chriſt; than (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before) any one of us can take that great <hi>Globe</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> into our hands.</p>
            <p>But <hi>God</hi> gives himſelf, and Jeſus Chriſt gives himſelf, by a free and abſolute will. And when he gives himſelf, he draws out by himſelf ſuch a turn of the Soul, back unto himſelf; that it cauſes the Soul by <hi>Faith</hi> to twiſt about him. He draws out himſelf ſo to it, that by <hi>Faith it Returns</hi> with ſuch a twiſt of the heart to <hi>himſelf,</hi> that it never <hi>uncloſes</hi> any more; that is the great and <hi>mighty Power of God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> Chriſt becoming <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to the Soul, draws out this <hi>Twiſting</hi> of the Soul about him; which the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls <hi>Faith;</hi> This laying hold upon him; this (as the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls it) is <hi>Leaning</hi> upon him; and <hi>Rolling</hi> of our <hi>ſelves</hi> upon him. Let no man deſpiſe theſe <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> has <hi>ſanctified them;</hi> It is Juſt as the <hi>Sun;</hi> it calls out the Eye, and the <hi>motions</hi> of the Eye, to <hi>Twiſt</hi> about it, and to unite with it, by ſeeing: In the very ſame <hi>manner;</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives <hi>himſelf;</hi> then he calls out this <hi>Faith,</hi> which is a <hi>Twiſt,</hi> and a hand of the <hi>Soul</hi> upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and about him. Now, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not give himſelf, and if <hi>God</hi> did not give himſelf; it were utterly <hi>impoſſible</hi> that <hi>Faith</hi> ſhould lay hold.</p>
            <p>Nay, though there is this <hi>Propoſition</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> every where held out; whoever believes in him, ſhall not <hi>periſh,</hi> but have <hi>Eternal life.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! Men do no more ſtir to this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> than a ſtone flyes up to the <hi>Sun,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhines upon it with its <hi>Beams.</hi> So <hi>I</hi> ſay, you may ſee plainly, that Men don't ſtir to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but when <hi>God</hi> draws near, and gives <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> draws near, and gives himſelf; then it is, that the Soul is drawn out to <hi>Chriſt</hi> again, and feels the coming of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the approach of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to it; and then <hi>turns it ſelf towards</hi> him; and <hi>then it catches about</hi> him; and then it begins to ſay, <hi>My Lord, and my God,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104490:23"/> as <hi>Thomas</hi> did, when he put his finger into the wounds that had been made in <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon the <hi>Croſs.</hi> This, <hi>I</hi> ſay, we ſhould ſeriouſly conſider; and to know this, if any of our Souls have been drawn to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> O know! That they had for ever layn ſtill, and ſunk as a ſtone, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had not come, and given himſelf to the Soul. <hi>I might</hi> give you many expreſſions to Explain this. <hi>To us a Child is given,</hi> (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. 6.) to whoever it is; as he was given to the world of Elect in General, ſo he is given in particular to every ſoul. <hi>Who loved me,</hi> and <hi>gave himſelf for me.</hi> And ſo, as <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks concerning love: <hi>We love him, becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> So we <hi>apprehend</hi> him, becauſe he firſt <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended us;</hi> As <hi>I</hi> have ſhewn you out of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12. If that <hi>I</hi> may <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that</hi> for which alſo <hi>I</hi> am <hi>apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> A man would never apprehend Chriſt, if he were not firſt apprehended by him. So ſaith the Church in the <hi>Song of Solomon; My Beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi> Firſt, he is mine; and then I am his. We ſhould never come to be Chriſt's; if Chriſt did not pleaſe to come, and to be our Husband.</p>
            <p>This certainly is the true freeneſs of the Grace of God. And, if you ſhould ſay, what neceſſity is there, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould thus draw out Faith? What need of Faith at all?</p>
            <p>I'll give you but <hi>a threefold Account,</hi> why there muſt be this Faith, <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> it does no more; and though it is no more in the great point of <hi>Righteouſneſs and Juſtification;</hi> yet ſtill it is moſt neceſſary it ſhould be, upon a four fold account.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Account is, 1ſt. Faith is neceſſary, as it is that <hi>Joyning,</hi> uniting act of the Soul, by way of <hi>Return</hi> to Chriſt giving himſelf to it, receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and <hi>poſſeſſing it ſelf of Chriſt,</hi> and of his Righteouſneſs; For as in our Law, though the foundation of the Title lye elſewhere, yet the Conſummating of the Right is by <hi>Livery and Seiſin;</hi> as they ſpeak; and though the <hi>Eſpouſal</hi> of a mean perſon to a Prince, is by his free Love, yet the Conſummation of the marriage is by her conſent, and <hi>acceptance</hi> Conſummate; ſo though Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs are free gift, yet Faith is neceſſary for our <hi>acceptance</hi> and till that be, Chriſt is not ours in Full ſenſe of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> It is true, Faith is choſen, and ſingled out, as that, which as it turns to Chriſt and his <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> moſt <hi>Diaphanouſly</hi> and moſt clearly, as through a thinneſt <hi>Tranſparency,</hi> ſhews the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt flowing from himſelf, above what Love, <hi>Repentance</hi> or any other graces or gracious actions can do, as being onely, as I have ſaid, <hi>Dependence,</hi> Receiving, Truſting; yet this Faith, as taking Chriſt and uniting to him, is more then <hi>manifeſtation;</hi> it is Conſummative of our Title; <hi>Christ ours, and we his: Chriſt is wiſdom</hi> to us in this wiſe Grace of Faith, and thus as in a Conſummate Title we are ſaid to be Juſtifyed by Faith. Faith is imputed to Righteouſneſs; but Chriſt our wiſdom, is alſo our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in higheſt Goſpel truth.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104490:24"/>
            <p>The ſecond account is, 2dly, Elſe it would not be for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and good of that Soul that hath Chriſt. It cannot be that Chriſt ſhould be a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and that the Soul ſhould not know it. Therefore, I ſay, it is neceſſary it ſhould be throughout the Soul made known by Faith. I confeſs, there is a time, and a long time, even from <hi>Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> till the Soul is called home to Chriſt, that it does not know it, till the time of bringing home to Chriſt. But I ſay, it cannot be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo; For then men ſhould be ſaved by Chriſt, and never know that they are ſaved by Chriſt. Then Chriſt would be no more the <hi>Saviour</hi> of his people, than he is the <hi>Saviour</hi> of ſtones, or inſenſible Rocks.</p>
            <p>We muſt therefore come to have a feeling, and knowing, <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is ours; Or elſe we could not receive his ſalvation. How ſhould we be the better within, if we did not know Chriſt? An <hi>understanding</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> Being, muſt have ſuch a knowledge of Faith, to know Chriſt. And therefore, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>I count all things but loſs for the Excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord.</hi> I muſt know him. Not that this Contributes any thing to our happineſs, but onely the feeling, and enjoying that happineſs: That happineſs is onely from God. But, as you know, a blind man is never the better in point of Light, and ſight, though the Sun be never ſo Glorious. <hi>Every one that ſeeth the Son,</hi> and believeth <hi>in him.</hi> We muſt ſee him; or elſe, we could not know he is ours; we could have no Enjoyment of him; our Souls would be ſtill, like unſenſible <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Marbles,</hi> if there were not this ſenſe by <hi>Faith,</hi> and the knowledge of Chriſt by believing. And therefore; it is a very great truth, that <hi>Faith</hi> is a manifeſtation to us, and within us, that Chriſt is ours. When our Souls receive the touches of his Love and grace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and we come to know and find the ſweetneſs; to taſte that the Lord is Gracious, and to know what a <hi>Pearl</hi> we have, in ſome meaſure; and that we find Chriſt is ours, and hath given himſelf for us.</p>
            <p>In the third place; there could not elſe be a manifeſtatory Glory. It is true; Chriſt is glorious, as a <hi>Saviour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But we could not Glorify him, if we did not know by <hi>Faith</hi> that he is ſuch a <hi>Saviour.</hi> This is that, that the ſoul makes its Boaſt in God by; this draws it to Glory in Chriſt, and to give all the Glory it can do to him; Becauſe it finds it is ſaved by him, and him alone. Now it is very <hi>Evident,</hi> God had no need of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from Angels, nor from men, to manifeſt his Glory by them. But it pleaſed the wiſdom and Grace of God, to declare his infinite Being, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Beings as Angels and men fitted with <hi>understandings</hi> to behold it. Why ſo, Chriſt had no need of our Glorifying of him; But yet it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Evident,</hi> that he is pleaſed to be Glorifyed by us; and that we Glorify him, by acknowledging all our ſalvation from him. And herein is <hi>Faith</hi> of great uſe; It gives Glory, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Abraham,</hi> was <hi>ſtrong in Faith, giving Glory to God, Rom.</hi> 4. So <hi>Faith</hi> gives Glory to the Righteouſneſs and <hi>Freeneſs</hi> of the Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt. And then,</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104490:24"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Fourth</hi> place; it is alſo neceſſary, upon this Account; (for, I am far (in all this diſcourſe) from that which is truly called <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> or <hi>Libertiniſm;</hi> I ſay as Faith looks outward, and from Chriſt, into holy Action, the knowledge that <hi>Faith</hi> gives is ſerviceable, in the hand of Chriſt to all holineſs, and purification of Life: To live to him; to live and to walk by <hi>Faith;</hi> to be every way ſelf-Reſigning according to <hi>that whole</hi> 11th <hi>Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavoured, with all briefneſs, to ſet out the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent nature of <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall but make one ſhort Application of it; And that is, to ſtir up all our hearts, in looking up to God, according to that great prayer <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 14, 15, 16. <hi>verſes. For this cauſe I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of whom the whole family in Heaven and Earth is nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he would grant you according to the riches of his Glory, to be ſtrengthned with might, by his ſpirit in the inner man.</hi> To what End?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by Faith.</hi> O look up to this! You ſee how <hi>Faith</hi> is indeed always called up by Chriſt, when he gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to any Soul; when he comes to dwell in any Soul, <hi>Faith</hi> muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him; it muſt embrace him; it muſt depend wholly upon him.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, O! That our hearts may be ſtrengthened by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Inner man. Alas! Our Inner man, you may ſee plainly by all that I have ſaid, is very weak and <hi>unfaithful;</hi> And it is confirmed by this expreſſion of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> how the Inner man would never draw in Chriſt; it would never hold him, if it came to him. Our Inner man is ſuch a falſe thing to the Great things of our Eternal ſalvation; it is ſuch a feeble weak thing, it would never be able to hold Chriſt. But the <hi>Spirit ſtrengthens the Inner man, That Chriſt may dwell in our hearts by Faith.</hi> Elſe, (I ſay) it could never (if you would give me leave to uſe ſuch a plain word as that) fetch in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And if he came, it would never hold him. Our Inner man <hi>must</hi> be ſtrengthened by the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> may dwell in us. And then, we go forward, to be <hi>rooted and grounded in the love of Chriſt;</hi> and to <hi>Comprehend that love of Chriſt which paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth knowledge, that we may be filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> hope, there is nothing that <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken, that can Juſtly offend any man's mind: for, it is fully to the ſenſe of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and of <hi>Scripture</hi> Reaſon, and it excludes all manner of looſeneſs and <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> of life.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is certainly ſanctification, to every one, to whom he is Juſtification; he gives the power of Holineſs. And <hi>Faith</hi> is made ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable. As <hi>I</hi> told you, the immanent acts, are thoſe whereby it ſtays within, and has Communion with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> wherein it has nothing but to depend and <hi>truſt</hi> in him. But then,</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104490:25"/>
            <p>It works outward, as they ſay of the works of God, <hi>Ad Extra.</hi> The Excellent acts of the Father, Son, and Spirit; they go out of themſelves. So Faith goes out to all the works of obedience.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if you would know what Faith is, when it works out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; <hi>I</hi> would propoſe to you, to Read that Chapter, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>How greatly Faith works outward.</hi> But <hi>Chriſt ſtill</hi> is the <hi>Author</hi> and finiſher. And when it comes to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it has nothing to do, but to truſt, and depend, and receive.</p>
            <p>And O! therefore, let us all <hi>bow our knees unto the Father of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that he would grant us, according to the Riches of his Glory, to be ſtrengthened with might, by his ſpirit in the Inner man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can never have ſuch a thing as Faith, if the Riches of Glory does not come in with it, and if the ſpirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> does not come in with it; And indeed, where the ſpirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes, he comes. And ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the ſpirit <hi>Elicits,</hi> (as they call it) and draws, and Brings the Soul to claſp about him, to lay hold upon him. He brings the Soul thus near to him, <hi>Just</hi> as the <hi>Load ſtone</hi> fetches in the <hi>Iron,</hi> and calls it to it ſelf. And ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes near to the Soul, He draws it near to himſelf, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <head>THE FAITH BY WHICH <hi>We are Iuſtified, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Fifth Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 5. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FRom what <hi>I</hi> have diſcours'd in the laſt Sermon, <hi>That we are Juſtified by Faith, in ſuch a ſenſe only, as that Nothing can be attributed to Faith, but only to</hi> Chriſt, Two Objections may ariſe, which <hi>I</hi> would anſwer, before <hi>I</hi> paſs on to the main Point <hi>I</hi> now intend.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104490:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. What then is it (may it be ſaid) in Faith, upon which <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> is attributed to Faith rather then to any other <hi>Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. I</hi> Anſwer; it is like taking poſſeſſion, the having <hi>Livery</hi> and <hi>Seizin</hi> in an Eſtate become ours, or like the conſent of a mean perſon in Marriage to a Prince.</p>
            <p>Or, indeed, to ſpeak yet more plain to our apprehenſion; if any one will give us a Gift; before we come to be really inveſted in that Gift; we muſt take it, and have it in poſſeſſion. And we have not a true Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to it elſe; tho it does not depend upon our taking; But it is only a Conſummative and Perfecting thing, that we take it into our <hi>poſſeſſion;</hi> we accept it from the giver, as his gift, and we take it into <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> as our own.</p>
            <p>And thus I ſay it is, and that we are <hi>Juſtifyed</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> And it ſeems to me, (except any one ſhall ſhew me wherein I am in a <hi>miſtake</hi> in thus ſaying) I ſhall <hi>conclude</hi> it to be the very ſenſe of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in all thoſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,</hi> that we are Juſtifyed by <hi>Faith,</hi> and live by <hi>Faith:</hi> Theſe things, I ſay, ſhew to us the <hi>worthleſſneſs</hi> of Faith in it ſelf; And yet that it is <hi>Conſummative</hi> and a <hi>Conſummation</hi> of our Title to Chriſt, and to his <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would only firſt anſwer one more ſeeming great objection againſt this repreſentation of Faith <hi>I</hi> have given, as if it were only the Imprint of Chriſt's gift of himſelf and his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to the Soul; why is it then ſo often ſaid, <hi>Repent</hi> and believe the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> And <hi>whoever believes</hi> in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we are called on as if it were our act, to believe?</p>
            <p>Now, to this, I Anſwer, that it is true; we are ſo: Though I am fully, by the grace of <hi>God,</hi> of that <hi>Judgment,</hi> that I have <hi>declared</hi> to you, concerning the nature of <hi>Faith:</hi> And that it is Chriſt, <hi>Imprinting</hi> his gift the gift of his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and of himſelf upon us. And yet for all that; I think my ſelf bound, in all the Diſcourſes of this grace of Faith to move you; to <hi>perſwade</hi> you; to Exhort you to receive, to preſs you to Believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Becauſe this is the <hi>Rational</hi> way that <hi>God</hi> doth deal with thoſe, as I have ſaid, he giveth <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>Rationality</hi> to; and becauſe this is that <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and for great and wiſe <hi>Reaſons,</hi> both to his <hi>Servants,</hi> whom he draws thus to believe by the <hi>obedience</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Faith to the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Goſpel: And in regard of thoſe, that do not believe, That he may <hi>Juſtify</hi> and vindicate himſelf, that he hath gone that way, which is proper unto the Soul of man: He hath drawn with the <hi>Cords of a man,</hi> and with the <hi>Bands of his Love,</hi> in offering Chriſt to them.</p>
            <p>I now come to what I propoſed in the next place; To ſhew you the great aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nce of Faith; the <hi>aſſurance</hi> of it, from theſe words of our Lord; <hi>They have known. They have known;</hi> And they have <hi>ſurely known.</hi> And yet, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it comes to be <hi>Explained,</hi> what this knowledge is; It comes to this; it is <hi>Believing.</hi> For, Pray obſerve the courſe of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104490:26"/> words, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17. 7. <hi>They have known.</hi> To know, is of great <hi>Certainty,</hi> and of great <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> And again, in the latter part of the vereſe. <hi>They have known ſurely, that I came out from thee;</hi> and they <hi>have believed that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> They have <hi>known</hi> ſurely; And yet when it comes to the iſſue; they have <hi>believed.</hi> Therefore I ſhall <hi>endeavour, I</hi> ſay, to make out to you the great <hi>Aſſurance of Faith.</hi> And <hi>I</hi> ſhall propoſe theſe four kinds of aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that Faith hath. And there are <hi>Scriptures</hi> very full, for each of them. <hi>I</hi>'ll lay them firſt, before you, together.</p>
            <p>The firſt aſſurance of Faith, is the <hi>aſſurance of underſtanding.</hi> So you find, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>That their hearts might be comforted, being knit together in love, and unto all riches of the full aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi> in the <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the myſtery of God, and of the father, and of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's the firſt aſſurance of Faith; the <hi>aſſurance</hi> of <hi>underſtanding;</hi> when all the <hi>great truths</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> that men are ready to ſay, how do you prove them?</p>
            <p>How will you make them out, either by ſenſe, or by Reaſon? How ſhall we know that theſe things are indeed true?</p>
            <p>Why now, when Chriſt and his Spirit do fix theſe truths upon Souls; they have Riches of the full aſſurance of <hi>underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond full aſſurance of Faith, it is in that great Point, of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, and peace of Conſcience by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For, if a man comes, and ſays to another, (As you know, men are ready to do) you talk at a ſtrange Rate: Do you know that your ſins are pardoned? Do you know, that <hi>God,</hi> and Chriſt have Done this? and that you ſhall be ſaved from wrath for ever?</p>
            <p>Obſerve now what the Apoſtle ſaith to this, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 22. <hi>Let us draw near with a true heart.</hi> You know, it is a phraſe in our <hi>Engliſh;</hi> ſuch a man, when we do ſpeak of him, as fearful, or a perſon of no valour; we ſay, he is a falſe-hearted man. And that man that is Reſolved and valiant, and great in Proweſs; we ſay, he is a man of a true heart, of a true valour.</p>
            <p>Now whereas, ſome are apt to think, that every man ſhould ſtand trembling, and doubting, and ſay, <hi>I</hi> don't know whether my ſins are pardoned, or not; <hi>I</hi> dare not be ſo bold or preſumptuous as once to ſay, <hi>I</hi> am ſure that <hi>I</hi> am freed from wrath to come.</p>
            <p>Why now (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Let us draw near with a true heart, having our heart ſprinkled from an evil conſcience, and our bodies waſhed with pure wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> So here's a ſecond great aſſurance of Faith.</p>
            <p>A Third aſſurance of Faith, is in this; O, what ſhall become of me for ever? What ſhall become of me when I dye? Where will be my dwelling? Where will be my Reception, my Receptacle for ever, when I go out of the world?</p>
            <p>Can I hope for ſuch a ſtate, as the <hi>Scripture</hi> Deſcribes Heaven to be? Can I bear up in thoſe hopes?</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104490:26"/>
            <p>Why then, Conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. latter part of the 11 ver. <hi>We, deſire, that every one of you do ſhew the ſame diligence, to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here you ſee is another aſſurance; the <hi>full aſſurance of hope</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our condition. Hope is the proper grace that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> inſiſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to the aſſurance of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, there is a fourth; In theſe three places I deſire you to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the word is one, and the ſame in the Greek in every one of them: It is <hi>Plerophoria;</hi> or full-ſail-aſſurance.</p>
            <p>There is a fourth aſſurance (which is very neceſſary to be conſidered) and that is the aſſurance of acting ſuitable, and agreeable to our Faith, when a man dares venture; when he dares <hi>Embarque,</hi> and engage his action, upon this very <hi>foundation</hi> of Faith.</p>
            <p>Now here (for, I would deal very clearly and faithfully in theſe points, and not <hi>pretend</hi> to any thing of proof, above what really is <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>) there is the <hi>Tantamount</hi> of it; but there is not the very word <hi>Plero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoria,</hi> or full aſſurance of Faith But, I ſay, very near to that very thing.</p>
            <p>The 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 10. 11, 12. Saith the Apoſtle (ſpeaking with great Earneſtneſs) <hi>wherefore alſo we pray always for you, that our God would count you worthy of his calling,</hi> and <hi>fulfill all the good pleaſure of his grace; and the work of Faith with power. The good pleaſure of his grace to be fulfilled; and the work of Faith to be fulfilled. Pleroſe,</hi> a word that bears part with the ſame word that <hi>Plerophoria.</hi> For there's the <hi>fulneſs.</hi> But then, in the full aſſurance ſignified by <hi>Plerophoria;</hi> there is the carrying of the ſayl: which ſignifies a ſayl that hath a full <hi>Gale</hi> upon it; and ſo carryes on the veſſel with a mighty ſwiftneſs. And here the fulneſs is ſignified, and the mighty Gale alſo, tho there be not the word; that he would <hi>fulfil the Work of Faith with Power. That the name of our Lord Jeſus Christ may be glorified in you, and you in him, according to the Grace of our God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now therefore, as I have laid before you the four full <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of Faith;</hi> the great Confidences and Aſſurances of Faith; ſo I would ſhew you what there is to bear up theſe great Aſſurances of Faith. For, It is not an ordinary Power that can bear up a Man, that hath nothing of it at all in himſelf, to bear up, <hi>I</hi> ſay, <hi>in this full aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of underſtanding.</hi> That, whereas men make ſuch a do, to prove the Truth of the Religion, and Chriſtianity of the Goſpel: If a Man comes in by Faith, and ſays, I cannot Reaſon; I cannot Diſpute; I can not Argue; I cannot talk like a Learned Perſon, concerning theſe things. But, bleſſed be God, I can do this; <hi>I can Believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So another comes, and ſays, O! I could never get ſuch a thing as this; the hopes of the Favour and Love of God in Chriſt; and the Pardon of my Sins.</p>
            <p>But when a Man comes under the mighty Power of Grace; to be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104490:27"/> filled with the Aſſurance of this by mighty Power; he is able to ſay, in ſome meaſure, <hi>I believe theſe things, Lord Help my unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſometimes God raiſes up his Servants to a Triumphant Aſſurance, even at the time of Dying, when they are in the greateſt Agonies of Body; yet they can ſay, <hi>I am ſure my Redeemer Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then, for the ſtate beyond the Line, beyond this Life; Who can tell this? Fleſh and Blood is ready to ſay, what there is in another World; who hath gone, and brought certain Accounts and Intelligences what the ſtate of the other World is?</p>
            <p>O! The full Aſſurance of Faith and Hope; it ſaith, <hi>I am ſure of an Inheritance Incorruptible, and that fades not away:</hi> Tho I cannot tell you, what it is; Yet I know I ſhall be like my Lord, for I ſhall ſee him as he is. And then,</p>
            <p>In the laſt place; ſaith a man, what, will you venture your ſelves? Will you venture to loſe all that you might Enjoy here in this World? and to pin your ſelves to a ſtrict way of Walking? Will you venture to deny your ſelves in your Pleaſures, in your Enjoyments here? You muſt lay down Eſtate, and Life; and leave all the dearneſs of Relations: Will you venture to do ſuch a thing as this?</p>
            <p>O! ſaith the Soul; if I have but the good pleaſure of my God, and the Work of Faith fulfilled in me with Power; I do not care how God calls me out, to glorify the Name of God, and of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>I'll begin to lay down the Account of all this to you; and that I ſhall do very briefly. There is but one place of Scripture, to which I refer; to ſhew you what it is that bears up Faith in all theſe Things: And it is that, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>I</hi> deſire, that you would pleaſe to ſet a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark: Every perſon that hears, and that does ſeriouſly deſire to wait upon God in this Diſcourſe; That you would ſet a Remark upon that Scripture I name to you, in the four Aſſurances of Faith, <hi>Whoſoever is born of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>overcometh the World: And this is the Victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith. Who is he that overcometh the World, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Son of God?</hi> O! But may the Soul ſay; Here's the Difficulty; How ſhall <hi>I</hi> do to Believe this, That Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God; That he came forth from God; and that God did ſend him? Why, ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>This is he that came by Water and Blood, even Jeſus Chriſt; not by VVater, but by Water and Blood. And it is the Spirit that beareth witneſs, becauſe the Spirit is Truth.</hi> For there are three <hi>that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the VVord, and the Holy Spirit; And theſe: three are one. And there are three that bear witneſs on Earth, the Spirit, and the VVater, and the Blood; if you receive the witneſs of Men, the witneſs of God is greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, Here is the thing that <hi>I</hi> ſhall endeavour to make out to you; That Faith, in all theſe Aſſurances, is born up by thoſe three, <hi>That bear witneſs in Heaven;</hi> Principally, and Supremely, <hi>The Father, the VVord, and the Spirit.</hi> And, by the <hi>Three, that bear witneſs on Earth; the</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104490:27"/> 
               <hi>VVater, and the Blood, and the Spirit.</hi> And indeed, the Undertaking is very large, and very great, to ſpeak of the things according to their Weight, according to their worth. Only, I deſire you to take notice, before I go on; That it is very Evident, the Apoſtle is ſpeaking of the Fulfilling the Work of Faith, <hi>to overcome the VVorld;</hi> and to give the Soul Victory through Chriſt: For, upon this occaſion All this comes on, What is it overcomes the World, but only our Faith? And ſo he goes on to the great Teſtimony, and the great Operations in thoſe that are Chriſts, and by which Faith is born up; <hi>If we receive the witneſs of Men, the witneſs of God is greater.</hi> It is not only greater in Value, but in this, that it can enter into the Hearts, into the Conſciences, into the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of his Servants.</p>
            <p>I begin therefore with the Firſt of theſe; And I ſhall ſhew you, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very reſpect, how <hi>the Father, the VVord, and the Spirit; and the VVater, and the Blood do VVitneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, concerning the full Aſſurance of underſtanding; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Jeſus Chriſt, in the firſt place; And then, concerning all the Truths of the Goſpel, in the ſecond place; And I deſire you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a diſtinction I gave you the laſt day; I told you, there are imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Acts of Faith, as they ſay; <hi>thoſe that remain and ſtay within;</hi> that's the meaning of the Word: There are Acts then, and Motions of Faith, when Faith ſtays within, in that great point of taking Chriſt. And then, There are Truths of the Goſpel that are <hi>Ad Extra,</hi> as they ſay; or without, that do not immediately concern that great point of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Chriſt, but flow from it.</p>
            <p>No I'll make this plain to you, by ſetting two points of Scripture before you; of which Faith has an aſſurance: But one is like Faith ſtaying at home, and within it ſelf, and within Chriſt, in the great point of <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Now, Here's this great Truth, That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World, to ſave the chief of Sinners: Sinners, of whom every one may ſay, <hi>I am chief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when Faith Acts upon this Truth; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of whom I am chief.</hi> And ſo, That he ſhed his Blood for ſinners, and gave himſelf a Sacrifice and an Attonement: All theſe are Truths properly within Faith and Chriſt: And when the Soul is upon them, it is at home with it ſelf; And Faith is alſo at home with Chriſt, and with the Soul in them. But now, here's another great Truth; That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is that does not <hi>Cut off his Right Hand, or Pull out his Right Eye, and cut off his Right Foot; he ſhall be caſt into Hell, where their VVorm dies not, and their Fire is not quenched.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is a great Truth of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And Faith hath aſſurance of this Truth. But yet, when it acts upon this Truth; (Pray obſerve) it does not ſtay within, <hi>properly</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and within it ſelf, in the point
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104490:28"/> of <hi>Believing:</hi> But it goes out, to a Truth that lyes without, as to the great point of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> So that, if you ſay, wherein is <hi>Faith Juſtifying</hi> Faith, in <hi>Relation</hi> to Truth? (I deſire that I may be underſtood) I ſay, when it is ask'd wherein is <hi>Faith Juſtifying Faith,</hi> as to the point of Truth?</p>
            <p>It is not in believing that whoſoever doth not <hi>cut off his Right hand, or pluck out his right Eye,</hi> ſhall be <hi>caſt into Darkneſs.</hi> It is true; this always is together with <hi>Juſtifying Faith:</hi> But it is not that, wherein Faith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Juſtifies. But all the Truths concerning the <hi>Blood and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of Chriſt; they are Truths that Faith acts upon, when it is in the great point of Juſtification, as it is acted by Chriſt and his Spirit; Now, this being not many times well Conſidered, It makes a great Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the point of <hi>Juſtifying Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, though it is true; It is ſaid (and I deſire it may be <hi>carefully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred;</hi> that no one may any way take offence; or <hi>mention</hi> what I ſay, to give offence) I ſay, that that Truth, that a man that does not <hi>cut off his hand,</hi> or <hi>pluck out his Right Eye</hi> (which means any Luſt) ſhall be <hi>caſt into Hell;</hi> is never ſeparated from true <hi>Juſtifying Faith.</hi> But I ſay again, that Faith acting upon that Truth; does not <hi>Juſtify;</hi> But acting upon the great Truth, wherein Jeſus Chriſt is held forth as a ſacrifice, a <hi>propitiation,</hi> a Mediator, an Interceſſor and Redeemer.</p>
            <p>But yet this is certainly true; that the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> give a mighty power to theſe great Truths, and to every Truth that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the Goſpel, but eſpecially with this great Principal Truth, that <hi>Jeſus is the Son of God,</hi> and hath layd down his life for ſinners.</p>
            <p>For, you ſee very plainly in this place that I have quoted to you; Pray, Conſider it, <hi>who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Son of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faith is therefore in its Immanent action, when it is upon this point, that <hi>Jeſus is the Son of God, and gave himſelf for Sinners.</hi> This is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Truth, that Faith fixes upon.</p>
            <p>But then, when it comes to that Truth, that <hi>without Holineſs, no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> that can never be ſeparated from this Truth, that <hi>Jeſus is the Son of God;</hi> when Faith acts upon that Truth, or any like it; <hi>Without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> It does not act like Juſtifying Faith, ſtrictly taken in that point of believing; Becauſe Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication flows onely from the Righteouſneſs, from the Blood, from the Obedience, from the Redemption of Jeſus Chriſt; And therefore, to Find a mighty power, To find the Soul Impregnated and fill'd out, in all the Truths that concern Jeſus Chriſt, and in all the other great Truths of the Goſpel, that Chriſt hath ſpoken; Here's the ſtrength, and the aſſurance of Faith; And it flows from God, in and through Chriſt. For, Jeſus Chriſt is the great and Principal Actor in the Soul's Receiving all Truth: I ſay, the great and the principal Actor. As
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104490:28"/> you may find, the ſtability of Faith, the great Ballance and Poize of Faith, that keeps it ſteady and even, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, and to day for ever. Be not carryed about with diverſe and ſtrange Doctrines: Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, and to day for ever:</hi> It is he that is the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega;</hi> As he ſaith himſelf. <hi>The Truth; the way, the Truth</hi> and <hi>the Life.</hi> He is (the) Truth. And the <hi>Son of the Father in Truth. And Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I would a little further clear to you this diſtinction of the Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent acts of Faith; and ſhew you whence I take the word You know, in that great myſtery of the Father, Son, and Spirit; Divines, when they treat of it; they ſay, that thoſe actions between the Father, and the Son, and the Spirit themſelves, and no Created Bing comes between; they call them, Immanent actions of the Father, the Word, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. As the Father <hi>begat</hi> and <hi>knoweth</hi> the <hi>Son;</hi> ſo the <hi>Son knoweth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and that he is <hi>begotten of him.</hi> The holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son: And the holy Spirit knows, and Glorifieth in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing <hi>the Father,</hi> and <hi>the Son,</hi> as proceeding from them. Now, while they are acting within in the Divine Being, the Father, the Son, and Spirit, one with another; Thoſe are called Immanent acts.</p>
            <p>But when they go outward, either to Angels, or men, or any of the Creatures; then they are called extra-acts; Or <hi>ad extra,</hi> or Tranſient acts; becauſe they go out from the Divine being to the Creature.</p>
            <p>I make uſe of it, to explain the Immanent acts of Faith: The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent acts of Faith, are upon Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and Blood; and not upon the Points of Repentance, or obedience, or Love, or ſelf Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation to Chriſt; But wholly, and ſolely in that point of Pardon of ſin, Peace of Conſcience, and deliverance from wrath to come.</p>
            <p>But, as I ſaid before; Take any of the great Truths of <hi>Scripture;</hi> and they are never ſeparated from that Juſtifying Faith. All the actions of Creation and Government of Providence; are never ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Divine Being, the Father, Word, and Spirit: Creation and Providence, you know are attributed to them all. And, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that this may much help your thoughts: Becauſe men diſcourſe promiſcuouſly; As if we were as well Juſtified by love to Chriſt, and by mortifying a Luſt, as by taking hold of the ſacrifice and Ranſom of Jeſus Chriſt; and as if one Truth were as eſſential to Juſtifying Faith, as another; Now, I acknowledge, they are never ſeparated: (To take off all Scandal and offence from men.) And yet I ſay, there's an Immanence in the act of Faith, when it is acting upon Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Second Point, that I would be ſomething more large in; And that is, concerning full aſſurance of Faith, in point of Conſcience, or the peace of Conſcience, and the Pardon of Sin, and the aſſurance that God is ours.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104490:29"/>
            <p>Now, if I could here make out to you, how that Aſſurance comes into the Soul; and how it is born up by Chriſt, and by the Father, and by the Spirit; I ſhould think it were to great Edification. I ſay, if I were in any meaſure able to make it out, according to the Excellency of the thing; I ſhall therefore go as far as the Lord ſhall pleaſe to aſſiſt by his Spirit in it.</p>
            <p>Therefore, the firſt thing that I ſhall ſay to you, by which a man comes to have an Aſſurance of the Pardon and Forgiveneſs of his Sins (I ſhall ſpeak it in the very Scripture Language.) It is,</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, By an immediate Voice of the <hi>Blood;</hi> I ſay, by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Voice of the <hi>Blood.</hi> And then,</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhew you, it is by the Voice of the <hi>VVater</hi> from Chriſt. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Third piace, By the Spirit. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Fourth place, that the <hi>Father</hi> from Heaven comes, and Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and Aſſures this Teſtimony of the <hi>Son,</hi> and of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in the <hi>Blood</hi> and in the <hi>VVater;</hi> Firſt, <hi>I</hi> ſay, it proceeds immediately. (For <hi>I</hi> would ſpeak of the things in the Order of Nature) from the Blood. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth ſo immediately ſpeak Peace to a Sinner, as the Blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Sufferings of Chriſt. And therefore, ſo many things are ſpoken of Chriſt; of his Sacrifice, and of his Death, and of his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; <hi>I</hi> may give you many places of Scripture that put moſt upon the Blood of his Sacrifice, as to our Senſe and Apprehenſion, than up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any thing: <hi>I</hi> ſay, upon the Blood of Chriſt: <hi>How much more ſhall the Blood Offered by the Eternal Spirit.</hi> (you know, Heb. 9) <hi>And the blood of Sprinkling that ſpeaketh better things than that of</hi> Abel, c. 12. And Heb. 10 24. <hi>Having boldneſs by the blood of Jeſus, to enter into the Holieſt. It is put upon the blood, the blood of the Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> Heb. 13. <hi>The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 John 1. <hi>VVho loved us, and waſhed in his blood,</hi> Rev. 1. and Rev. c. 7. <hi>They have waſhed their robes white in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks proportionably in this 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>There are Three that bear witneſs in Heaven; the Father, the VVord and the Spirit.</hi> And then there is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>VVater,</hi> and the <hi>Blood.</hi> The Blood, it hath an immediate Voice. <hi>And this is he</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>that came by water and by blood, not by water only:</hi> Pray obſerve that: it puts an Emphaſis upon the <hi>Blood. Not by VVater only, but by VVater and Blood.</hi> So <hi>I</hi> ſay, whenever our Souls come indeed to have the Aſſurance of the Pardon of Sin, and of Peace with God; it is by Blood: The Blood of Jeſus, which is <hi>carried into the Holy Place not made with hands.</hi> We are Purged by the Blood Offered by the Eternal Spirit: We have Confidence by the Blood of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>O! therefore, when Chriſt is pleaſed to ſend out the mighty <hi>Effluxes</hi> the <hi>Efluviums</hi> of his blood; when he ſends them out, and draws and twiſts and brings back the Conſcience, and the Heart upon the Blood of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104490:29"/> Chriſt, when he is pleaſed to do thus; Thoſe ſtrong Acts upon the blood of Chriſt, they do as it were Recoil and come back upon the Soul, and upon the Conſcience, with the aſſurance of the pardon of ſin in that blood. Therefore, bleſſed is he that hears the voice of the blood of Chriſt; that hears in his own Conſcience, the <hi>blood of ſprinkling, ſpeaking better things, than that of Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the firſt thing. Becauſe I treat as briefly as I can of it; I come to the ſecond thing, and that is,</p>
            <p>To give you an account of the forgiveneſs of ſins, comeing in by the <hi>Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I confeſs, I ſhall give ſomewhat another Interpretation, than I have known given concerning <hi>Water.</hi> For, I look upon the water, not as ſome would, very Chilly and Coldly <hi>underſtand</hi> it of Baptiſm: except that <hi>ſpiritual Baptiſm</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which I always deſire to magnify; or that it is meerly <hi>Sanctification,</hi> which the <hi>Generality</hi> of <hi>Interpreters</hi> give it to be: But by water, <hi>I understand</hi> the very <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt <hi>ſeparated</hi> from his ſufferings: That great obedience, which was like a River Pure as Chriſtal that ran through the whole obedience of Jeſus Chriſt, from the very beginning to the end.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſon why I take it ſo, and not to be <hi>ſanctification,</hi> is this; becauſe, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in this 5 Chapter of the 1ſt Epiſtle of <hi>John. This is he that came by water, and by blood. Not by water onely, but by water and blood.</hi> He came himſelf by water, and by blood: He himſelf came. This [He] take notice of him; He came by water, and he came by blood He came by the water of a pure and perfect Righteouſneſs; in which, there was nothing at all of <hi>Imperfection,</hi> or ſoil, or the leaſt of blemiſh; He came by this water. And ſo you find the obedience of Chriſt is often mentioned in <hi>Scripture,</hi> I ſhall give you that place for all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 18. Saith the Apoſtle there; <hi>By the obedience,</hi> He ſpeaks often of the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt. <hi>But by the obedience of one ſhall many be made Righteous,</hi> ver. 19 And <hi>by the Righteouſneſs of one; The offence</hi> of one; and <hi>the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of one; The Diſobedience of one;</hi> and the <hi>obedience of one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So, Obedience and Righteouſneſs, they are of one and the ſame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. And <hi>the comeing by water,</hi> I ſay, is comeing by the perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Righteouſneſs of the whole nature, and action, and performance of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, when the Soul is ſaluted (as I may ſo expreſs it) by Chriſt, with this obedience in his hand; when he comes, ſaith Chriſt to the Soul, I have obeyed; I have fulfilled all Righteouſneſs; I have done always the things pleaſing in the ſight of my Father; there was no guile found in my mouth; there was no ſin found in me; without ſin, in the midſt of all the Temptations that ever could be Congregated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104490:30"/>
            <p>Here therefore, take this obedience of mine; and let it ſtand againſt thy diſobedience; againſt thy many ſins; thy many provocations and Tranſgreſſions; I have come by pureſt water. And ſo there <hi>ſhall be a fountain opened for ſin and for uncleanneſs. Zech.</hi> 13. 1. And he leads them to the <hi>Fountains of living water,</hi> in his own Righteouſneſs, in his own obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And having the <hi>heart ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy waſhed with pure water;</hi> That is, not of ſanctification as we might be very apt to underſtand it: I ſay, not principally; I never exclude ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; but not principally. But that purity of the obedience of Chriſt, by which <hi>we are made the Righteouſneſs of God through him.</hi> And when this water ſpeaks in this ſenſe, that I have now layd down to you; It gives that great aſſurance againſt the fear of Hell, wrath and Eternal condemnation, for we are Righteous by it. The ſecond thing (in which I will be very brief) is, the ſpirit that gives witneſs.</p>
            <p>You know, that is a general allowed Doctrine, that the <hi>Spirit of God ſeals up to the day of Redemption. It is the Earneſt</hi> of it in the aſſurance of the pardon of ſin, in the witneſs of abſolution that it gives; It is the <hi>Spirit of Adoption and the Spirit of promiſe. After ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe, which is the earnest of our Inheritance; The Spirit it ſelf bears witneſs with our Spirits, that we are the children of God.</hi> And hence ariſes the great aſſurance of Faith. O! When a man can find the word of the Spirit within that word in his own Soul, that his iniquities are pardoned, and his ſins forgiven; The Spirit is a mighty witneſs: For the Spirit is Truth. He is able to ſpread his witneſs throughout the whole Soul; to ſeal up the whole Soul to himſelf. But then, the laſt thing that I will ſpeak of, is this; There comes in that mighty Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative and original act of the Father; ſaying, I have forgiven thy ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>I</hi> have pardoned thy ſin. And <hi>I</hi> look upon it to be conveyed, eſpecially in that voice that we have in the three Evangeliſts, <hi>Matt.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>There came a voice from Heaven:</hi> And, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, from the <hi>Excellent Majeſty,</hi> ſaying, <hi>this is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> That is, <hi>I</hi> have accepted him for a Ranſom; <hi>I</hi> have accepted his obedience; <hi>I</hi> have freely forgiven iniquity for his ſake; for he is my ſelf; he is my Son; he is mine; and therefore I do it freely; and yet <hi>I</hi> do it for his ſake; Becauſe he has given a Recompenſe, a ſatisfaction to Juſtice. And ſo the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Who hath made us accepted in the beloved. And, in whom we have redemption in his blood, the forgiveneſs of ſins.</hi> And ſo it is ſaid by Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>The Father loveth me; And whatſoever ye ask in my Name, the Father will do it for you.</hi> There comes in the great Evidence, Teſtimony, and Aſſurance of the Fathers <hi>free accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and free abſolution through him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To cloſe therefore thus much as I have begun to ſay, from theſe words, in brief application.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104490:30"/>
            <p>This firſt Application is this; That you would ſeriouſly conſider, whether you have Faith or not?</p>
            <p>You may ſay, How ſhall I know? Why conſider it, as I have now repreſented it to you: It is a mighty Power from Chriſt; it is a mighty power from his Spirit in all the Truths of God; Eſpecially, thoſe Truths that concern Jeſus Chriſt. But juſt as I opened to you in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of this Diſcourſe; That Faith, it is a new Underſtanding to us: We have as Men (you know) an underſtanding, endued with Reaſon. And therefore, we all ſay, let me hear Reaſon, and then I'll be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded: And every Wiſe Man, whenever he ſpeaks, he endeavours to ſpeak Reaſon; Therefore God hath given to man ſuch a thing as he calls Reaſon: He hath Endued the Underſtanding with that great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Reaſon. And, if a Man be a Natural; you know that is a man in whom Reaſon cannot act; becauſe ſome of the Organs of the Body are not prepared to let Reaſon have its courſe; 'Tis plain that's the meaning of men being Naturals.</p>
            <p>It may be, you may think, they have not ſo good a Soul; but that's a miſtake: Only there are not Organs fit for the working of Reaſon; And therefore you know, when we look upon ſuch a one, we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a vain thing, to Diſcourſe with ſuch a one; becauſe we know he has no Reaſon: Or a Mad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>an; it is but loſs of time to Diſcourſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to him; becauſe there is ſuch a Diſturbance, and ſuch a kind of jumble in the Brain that Reaſon cannot have its courſe.</p>
            <p>So I ſay, if we would conſider, a Man, in Goſpel ſenſe, he is juſt like a meer Natural, or like a Mad-man, or like a very Brute, if he has not a Light of Faith: For, Faith is a New Light, and a New Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And therefore it is very obſervable, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>That we may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>from unreaſonable and wicked men: For all men have not faith.</hi> If a Man be unreaſonable, you can have no place in him by the powers of Reaſon. Now (ſaith the Apoſtle) I look upon a man in Goſpel-ſenſe, juſt like a Natural, or like a Mad-man; or like a very Brute, if he has not a Light of Faith, he is an unreaſonable Perſon, when he has not Faith; For, <hi>all men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have not Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the word that is uſed in the Origninal, is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is very well known among the Learned, to be a word proper to Philoſophy; They ſay, if a Man has not the Powers of Reaſon, or does not ſpeak accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them; he is an abſur'd man, or an unreaſonable Man; he is a Man that hath no <hi>Topicks;</hi> Now, ſaith the Apoſtle, he is an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Man; he has no <hi>Topicks</hi> with him: And why? becauſe he has no Faith.</p>
            <p>So I ſay, a Man without Faith, is a Man without Goſpel <hi>Topicks:</hi> You cannot ſpeak to him upon the <hi>Topicks</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, with any Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; becauſe he has not Faith.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104490:31"/>
            <p>O! Therefore, Let us conſider, how ſweet is the Diſcourſe of Chriſt to us? How impreſſive upon us? How do our Souls go out to him, and act upon him? As you know, the mind of man, even in worldly things, is acting according to Reaſon, and all the Powers of Reaſon; So we ſhould be always Acting upon the Goſpel, and upon Chriſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, by all the Powers of Faith. And therefore this I would deſire you, to mind in the immanent Truths; in thoſe Truths wherein <hi>Faith</hi> is in its immanent Acts, principally upon Chriſt, and Righteouſneſs in him, and Pardon of ſin in his <hi>Blood.</hi> O! conſider, how your Souls are Acted to him: And ſo go from thence to All Truth; for there's no ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as I have ſhewn you: The ſame Omnipotency of God that is in the Father, and the Son, and the Spirit is that ſtrength that went out, and Created this World, Acts <hi>ad extra,</hi> or without the Father, Son and Spirit: Why, ſo the Faith, which in its immanent Acts ſtays upon Chriſt and his Blood, it alſo paſſes and goes out upon all the Truths of Holineſs and Obedience. But then,</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing (with which I would conclude) is this; That you mind theſe mighty Powers that Act Faith: O! mind all the greatneſs of the Blood, and of the Water; and the Witneſs of the Father, and the Word, and the Spirit. It is a great Scripture that I led you to the laſt day, and (with which I'll cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſcourſe,) which ſhews you, that the mighty Power of Faith is from God, and from Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>For this cauſe I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of whom the whole Family in Heaven amd Earth is Named; That he would grant unto you, according to the riches of his Glory, to be ſtrength'ned with Might, by his Spirit in the inner man; that Chriſt may dwell in your Hearts by Faith.</hi> Here you have the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> joyned in this great Power of <hi>Faith, that ye being rooted and grounded in Love</hi> (that is, in the Love of Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>may be able to comprehend.</hi> In your Love to him, I underſtand that firſt groundedneſs in Love to Chriſt; A Love that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains us to live to him that dyed for us, and then, may be able to comprehend with all Saints what is the breadth and length, and heigth; And to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth Knowledg.</hi> O! That great Miſtery of the Goſpel; And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cularly, <hi>that we may know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth Knowldg;</hi> And hereby we may come to be <hi>filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! who is able to bring this great work into our Hearts? VVhy, the Apoſtle therefore concludes. <hi>Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly above all that we ask or think, according to the Power that worketh in us;</hi> It is he that <hi>works in us;</hi> Pray take notice of that; Rememember that he works above all that <hi>we ask or think:</hi> And yet it is a <hi>Power works in us;</hi> that we may find, and ſee it, and have experience of it: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him be Glory</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the Church by Jeſus Chriſt, throughout all Ages, World without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the fifth Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104490:31"/>
            <head>THE FAITH BY WHICH <hi>We are Iuſtified, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Sixth Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 5. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FRom theſe words, <hi>I</hi> have pitch'd upon that great point and Doctrine of Juſtifying Faith: Or, of that Faith by which we are Juſtifyed.</p>
            <p>And this Faith, it eyes Chriſt, in a Peculiar manner. As <hi>I</hi> prov'd from <hi>John</hi> 17. 7, 8. <hi>Far, they have known</hi> (concerning me) that all things <hi>whatſoever thou haſt given me, are of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For, I have given unto them the words, which thou gaveſt me; and they have received them,</hi> (as ſo given unto me) <hi>and have known ſurely, that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didſt ſend me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here is a Conſtant Eye of Faith upon Chriſt. As <hi>I</hi> told you, there had never been ſuch a Notion of Faith, in <hi>Scripture-ſenſe,</hi> in <hi>Goſpel ſenſe,</hi> if it had not been for Chriſt; if he the Mediator had not been given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken of it, as it is Faith, by which we are juſtified, And the Grounds why it is Faith, that juſtifies here meant: (which <hi>I</hi> had not, mentioned before to you, but rather depended upon other <hi>Scriptures</hi> for) <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you now, <hi>viz.</hi> Why this Faith or believing is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Faith that juſtifies. Even out of that <hi>John</hi> 17. 7, 8. And the Reaſon <hi>I</hi> give for it, is, becauſe it is the Faith upon which Chriſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes: Pray, obſerve it, Chriſt Intercedes for believers, upon the Faith that believers <hi>know ſurely,</hi> and <hi>believe,</hi> concerning Jeſus Chriſt. For, in the very next words, you may obſerve it. <hi>I pray for them (ſaith he) I pray not for the world.</hi> So he intercedes for them; <hi>They have known,</hi> and <hi>believed,</hi> that Chriſt did ſurely come forth from God; and that all things of Chriſt are Divine, infinitely Divine; Originally Divine. Now therefore, upon whatſoever Chriſt intercedes; (Pray, Conſider) In the very ſame line our foundation for Righteouſneſs and acceptance through
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104490:32"/> Chriſt, reſts: His juſtifying Righteouſneſs and Redemption, and his interceſſion run all upon one line together; That's a plain point; they go together. <hi>I</hi>'ll give you but two places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> becauſe <hi>I</hi> would not prevent my ſelf, in what <hi>I</hi> have eſpecially to diſcourſe of. One is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>It is plain by all <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the blood of Chriſt is that great price of our Redemption; And that we are juſtified freely by the Grace of God, God <hi>Setting forth Chriſt, as a Propitiaton through Faith in his blood.</hi> Now you ſhall find that Chriſt <hi>entred by his blood into Heaven. Heb.</hi> 9. 12. <hi>But by his own blood he entred in once into the holy place, having obtained eternal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for us.</hi> Chriſt intercedes now in Heaven, and in the Holy place; into that <hi>Holy place made without hands,</hi> He entred to interceed. And again, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>Chriſt entred not into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into heaven it ſelf, now to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us.</hi> So that he intercedes plainly upon <hi>his blood;</hi> For where he intercedes he entered by his blood. And in 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 1. You alſo have the advocateſhip, and the <hi>Propitiation</hi> of Chriſt Joyn'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>My little children, theſe things write I unto you, that ye ſin not. And if any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father</hi> (viz.) <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous; And he is the Propitiation for our Sins,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is the clear ground I bottom this Truth upon: Upon what Chriſt intercedes, That is certainly Juſtifying. Now he intercedes upon the Faith of Believers. <hi>I pray for them, I pray not for the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> viz. <hi>For them who know ſurely, and believe in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have endeavoured to open Faith alſo to you ſo, that you may have a right underſtanding, that Faith does not Juſtify, as it is an Act of ours, or a Grace in us, or any thing in us; but only by its receiving the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I came to ſpeak of the Aſſurance of Faith. They have known: And they have ſurely known: <hi>And they have believed that thou didſt ſend me.</hi> Knowledg, or as the Learned ſpeak, and the great Men of Reaſon call it, Science, is the higheſt degree of Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Now this our Lord attributes to Faith, in that <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>They have known.</hi> For, Chriſt did not come meanly down, when he had ſaid, <hi>They have known,</hi> and then ſaid, <hi>They believed. But Faith</hi> is a furely <hi>knowing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I propoſed in the laſt Diſcourſe, to ſpeak of the <hi>Aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Faith,</hi> as it is a <hi>full Aſſurance of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> as I opened to you from <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>A full aſſurance of Faith,</hi> in the Pardon and Forgiveneſs of Sin: As I opened to you from, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 22.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>A full aſſurance of Hope.</hi> That, <hi>I</hi> did not ſpeak to before.</p>
            <p>But this, of all things, is moſt generally agreed, That the Servants of Chriſt may come to a full Aſſurance of Hope; No one will deny that to a Chriſtian, that he ſhould have a full Aſſurance of Hope now,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104490:32"/> and when he comes to Die, I ſay, of hope. Men will ſay, you may may hope; but you muſt not take upon you to be Aſſured beyond Hope.</p>
            <p>Now, indeed, <hi>Full Aſſurance of Hope</hi> is a very great Aſſurance, is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and excellent kind of Aſſurance. I might give you ſeveral Scriptures that ſpeak of this: As, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3. He calls it a <hi>Living Hope. Bleſſed be the God, and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath begotten us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain unto a living hope.</hi> We Tranſlate it, <hi>a lively Hope;</hi> But, if <hi>Living,</hi> will Agrandize the thing, and make it more Emphatical, the Original is, <hi>a living Hope,</hi> A hope that does not die, when we die; that does not die, when our Spirits are Languid, and our Eyes are ready to cloſe, and all the Terrors of Death are about us; yet this Hope will ſurvive.</p>
            <p>So the Apoſtle calls it; <hi>A good Hope through Grace; and a Hope that makes not aſhamed;</hi> That's another Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>And now, this great <hi>Aſſurance of Hope;</hi> you ſhall ſee on whom, or wherein the Apoſtle places it, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 27. laſt words of that verſe, which is <hi>Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory.</hi> So as I have ſhew'd you all along, Faith is wholly depending upon Chriſt; And all its Power and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency is in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now, can you have a fuller Expreſſion, <hi>That the full aſſurance of Hope; in Chriſt? Christ in you the hope of Glory.</hi> It is he himſelf that bears up this Hope; Alas! This Hope could no more Live, than the <hi>Hope of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> calls it) that is but like a <hi>Spiders Web;</hi> And that is but like a Stream cut off by the Drought of <hi>Summer,</hi> So would Hope be: But Chriſt is in his Servants the Hope of Glory, therefore their Hope Lives.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I have deſigned otherwiſe the Diſcourſe at this time; and that another great point is before us, I ſhall Addreſs my ſelf wholly to that: And that is,</p>
            <p>The Aſſurance of Holy Action: <hi>The full Aſſurance.</hi> Which I ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in a former Diſcourſe (upon the Generals I was to lay down) upon that of the Apoſtle, in the 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 11. Wherefore alſo we <hi>Pray always for you, that our God would count you worthy of his calling, and fulfil, that he would give you (a Plerophoria) all the good pleaſure of his goodneſs, and the work of Faith with Power, that the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be Glorified in you, and ye in him, according to the grace of our God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here every one may ſee plainly, that here is a mighty work of God, through the Heart, into the Lives and Converſations of his People, and that it is carried on with a full ſail by God.</p>
            <p>And then, as I told you in the 11th to the <hi>Heb.</hi> the Apoſtle goes throughout that Chapter, upon the Action of Faith. And therefore, if any one would Expound (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid to you) that in the 2d of <hi>James; A man is Juſtified not by Faith only, but by works,</hi> He ſhould compare it with this, of the Apoſtle, in the 11th to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> For there are the works of Faith Recorded and Recollected all along; <hi>By which the Elders obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a good report,</hi> a great Fame, a great Renown.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:104490:33"/>
            <p>Therefore, for the opening of this to you, becauſe indeed, it is a diffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cult point; and that which ſeems to ſhake all that I have ſpoken of our being Juſtified, not by Faith, as a work, but only as Chriſt chooſes to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the Soul to himſelf; and ſo to Communicate his Righteouſneſs, his Obedience, and the Value and Merit of his Sufferings by Faith; for when the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> ſhall lay down in ſuch expreſs terms, that a Man is Juſtified, not by Faith only, but by VVorks, and ſhall Diſcourſe it ſo, as he has done, in that <hi>James</hi> 2. 14. to the very end of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; It looks like a very great Objection; And the Enemies of Free Grace, and of the Juſtifying Grace of God, by his own Righteouſneſs, in Jeſus Chriſt make that Chapter (as I may ſay) the Top-gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant of all their Diſcourſe: It is the great and mighty Fort, to which they retire, upon all occaſions. Therefore theſe three Heads of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I hope, within the limits of Time that is alloted, tho it may ſeem ſomething ſtrait, to make out to you.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all; I would lay down to you, what are properly the works of Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I would ſhew you how the works of Faith are Dependent upon Chriſt, and upon his Righteouſneſs. And then,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>I</hi> would clear to you, how the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> Diſcourſes ſo much of VVorks, and that <hi>Faith</hi> only can do us no good; To clear that to you; and ſo to conclude with a brief Application of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> begin with the firſt, and that is to ſhew you the VVorks of <hi>Faith</hi> in general; and <hi>I</hi> ſhall do little more than point and direct your Thoughts to theſe great concernments; becauſe there will not be opportunity to handle them ſo fully and at large.</p>
            <p>The firſt kind of the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is this.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Acts of Faith, which do immediately concern our Receiving of Jeſus Chriſt, and the taking of himſelf, and his Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe (as I told you) might be called the immanent Acts of Faith; Thoſe neareſt, cloſeſt, privateſt Acts of Faith between Chriſt and the Soul; betwixt Chriſt himſelf, and the Soul it ſelf. For, I look upon it thus; and I deſire you to mind it.</p>
            <p>Whatever Faith is not the <hi>Faith of God's Elect, of God's Operation;</hi> A Faith of the Operation of God, it certainly miſſes in this firſt Act; Pray conſider, in this firſt Act of taking Chriſt: It is certain, the firſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of Faith is in Uniting to Chriſt; in taking him for our Head, for our Husband; in laying hold upon his Righteouſneſs, as in a Reflex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Act of the Soul, its taking, receiving, Chriſt giving himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now, a falſe Faith miſſes here; it does not take Chriſt; It thinks, it takes him, and does not take him. It is but Faith in a Dream, as the Prophet ſpeaks; The Hungry Man dreams <hi>that he Eats, and he awakes, and behold, he is Empty; and he Dreams he Drinks, and wakes, and finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſcorched with thirſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:104490:33"/>
            <p>So a Man Dreams he takes Chriſt, but he miſſes him; <hi>And lo, nothing is in his hand;</hi> I ſhall preſently ſpeak, how far we may Judg by the Action of Faith, whether we have been right in the firſt Act; But there has been, as they ſay, an Error in the Foundation; an Error in the firſt Concoction, as Phyſitians ſpeak, and cannot be mended: So there has been an Error in taking Chriſt; and Error in the Foundation becomes Error in the whole courſe of a Mans Building. A man ſays, he has taken Chriſt, and lives under the Power of his Luſts, and the Power of the World, Becauſe he never look Chriſt aright.</p>
            <p>Men will ſay, Here you are miſtaken in your Profeſſion; That you cannot live Holily, which your Profeſſion binds you to.</p>
            <p>But I ſay, if the thing were but well traced, and enquired into, it would be found, here was the great miſs, that your firſt Action flew off, and did not rightly take Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The 2d Chapter of <hi>John,</hi> is a Scripture that will clear this, that a Man may take Chriſt by a falſe Action, and loſe him in the very firſt Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the firſt beginnings by a miſtake.</p>
            <p>As now, it is in Nature, in the forming of an <hi>Embrio</hi> in the Womb; If there be a falſe formation, a monſtrous formation in the VVomb, there's an irregularity all along the Life. So, if Faith be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in its firſt Act, in ſuppoſing it takes Chriſt, and does not; that Error cannot be mended. The Latter Errors may be more apparent than the firſt, but the firſt is the cauſe of all, <hi>John</hi> 2. 23, 24, 25. <hi>Now when he was in</hi> Jernſalem <hi>at the Paſſover, in the Feaſt-day, many believed in his name, when they ſaw the Miracles that he did.</hi> One would have thought this was true Faith (as the great Men of Reaſon ſay) becauſe they were brought over to believe, by ſeeing the Miracles of Chriſt. <hi>But Jeſus did not commit himſelf unto them, becauſe he knew all men; And needed not that any ſhould Teſtify of man, for he knew what was in man.</hi> If he did not commit himſelf to them, we may very well underſtand, he did not Unite himſelf to them: He knew it was not that <hi>Faith,</hi> to which he United himſelf and his Righteouſneſs. Chriſt does not commit himſelf to a Faith, that is not indeed, as I ſaid before, <hi>a Faith of God's Elect, and the like pretious Faith,</hi> and that is not given by that Divine Lot of Grace, as the Expreſſion is, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1. that I have formerly ſpoken to you of; <hi>To them who have obtained by Lot,</hi> by this Divine <hi>Lot like precious Faith with us, according to the Righteouſneſs of God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I know we cannot look into this, but by the Divine Spirit, and by feeling the twiſtings of the Soul about Chriſt, through that great Opperation of God upon us: But this we may ſee plainly, Chriſt did <hi>not commit himſelf to them;</hi> So he does not commit his Righteouſneſs, his Propitiation, his Redemption; he does not commit it, but where he ſees a Faith, which he himſelf hath given, that is indeed, of the true and excellent Alloy; For, he knows at the very firſt: He ſees many that pretend to Believe, and that think they Believe; but he knows very well where their Faith
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104490:34"/> is wrong, and where it loſes that great Prize, that Pearl of <hi>Price</hi> that it is to obtain: He himſelf not committing or giving himſelf, knows a true Action of Faith in Receiving him will not follow; for that's the firſt Action of Faith to Receive Chriſt giving himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Second kind of the Actions of Faith, they are thoſe, that though they are not immediately as the firſt Acts of taking of Chriſt by Faith; yet they immediately Reſult, and Riſe up; When any Man hath taken Chriſt, there are ſome Actions that do immediately Reſult, and Ariſe; They bear the Hiew, they carry the Complexion they have upon them the Lineaments of the Death, of the Dying of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; They have ſuch peculiar Reſpects to his Blood, to his Death, to his Redemption.</p>
            <p>I would inſtance in two of theſe we find in Scripture-Saints. And then <hi>I</hi> ſhall draw out in brief Expreſſions, the general Actions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, according to their pattern.</p>
            <p>The firſt is that in the 11 Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> it is ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> v. 28. <hi>Through Faith he kept the Paſſover, and the ſprinkling of Blood, leſt he that destroyed the firſt born, ſhould touch them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he did by faith; God commanded him indeed to <hi>keep the Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over:</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi> had an Eye upon the Redemption of Chriſt in it; <hi>And by Faith he kept the Paſſover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So every Act of the Soul, by which it makes Recourſe to Chriſt upon all occaſions, after it hath taken him; it is like keeping the <hi>Paſſover;</hi> Every Act, <hi>I</hi> ſay, wherein we do eſpecially depend upon the Blood of Chriſt, and make cloſe Recourſe, and Application to it; it is an Action Reſulting from true, ſaving, Juſtifying faith; that true faith, by which we are Saved and Juſtified: For, ſo indeed, <hi>I</hi> obſerve; tho we call it Juſtifying faith, the Scripture never calls it ſo; But the faith by which we are Juſtified: To make good that point that <hi>I</hi> have always preſs'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; that we are not <hi>Juſtified by Faith,</hi> as an Act; But, we are Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied only as the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is given to it, for that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs alone is our Juſtification.</p>
            <p>But this I ſay, there are Acts of the Soul, by which it does make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Chriſt, and to his Blood.</p>
            <p>Another Example; and I chooſe to give it you, becauſe it is Seated in that of the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> that is made the great Objection againſt the faith by which we are Juſtified, through the Righteouſneſs and Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation of Chriſt, <hi>James</hi> 2. 21. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>our Father, Juſtified by works, when he had offered</hi> Iſaac <hi>his Son upon the Altar? Seeſt thou how faith wrought with his Works, and by works was faith made perfect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is the thing that <hi>I</hi> obſerve to you; The Offering of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> it was as great a Converſant Act about the Death, Blood and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crifice of Chriſt, as any could poſſibly be repreſented in Scripture to us. For, there could not be a greater Type and Repreſentation of the Father giving
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104490:34"/> his Son to Die for Sinners, and to become a Sacrifice for them, than that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Affectionate Father of <hi>Iſaac, Offering up his Son</hi> Iſaac. Therefore the Apoſtle uſes this for an Argument of a Working faith. This was a Work of Faith indeed; it was not a work of Faith, taking Chriſt; but it was a work of Faith, converſant about the Death and Sacrifice of Chriſt. And therefore the Apoſtle is expreſs in it, <hi>Seeſt thou how Faith wrought with his works?</hi> This was a great act, in which Faith wrought mightily, when <hi>Abraham offered up Iſaac.</hi> But 'twas not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a work of Moral obedience, as the work of Faith in Chriſt, if we Conſider the Greatneſs and excellency of it, and the Eye it had to Chriſt, though it was a high act of obedience of ſelf Reſigning alſo.</p>
            <p>So I ſay there are many acts, which are Converſant about taking Chriſt, and yet are not taking him, as when a man layes himſelf low be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, after his taking Chriſt, and pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es his whole hope and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in the Blood of Chriſt. When Man, in Prayer, lifts up his Soul to God, through the Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt; here's an Act of Faith.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Acts of Faith, they are not taking of Chriſt; but they are Converſant about Jeſus Chriſt, and his Redemption taken; and many ſuch there are.</p>
            <p>The Third kind of the works of Faith is, when Faith goes out into the Noble and Heroick Acts, that are more extraordinary in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, like to the Dying of Chriſt, and the way of Juſtifying Sinners, that God has taken, by the Death of Chriſt: When they in their kind, and in their Degree, bear an Image of that extraordinary.</p>
            <p>Theſe I look upon to be the works peculiarly of Faith. So in the 2d of <hi>James,</hi> Abraham's <hi>Offering</hi> Iſaac; which was an extraordinary Act; if you look upon't in the way of Obedience, and ſuch a one, as could not be accounted for, according to the Rules or Standards of Reaſon.</p>
            <p>What! ſhould <hi>Abraham</hi> Receive from God, an only Son, and then go and Sacrifice him to God, and be ſatisfied, and Reſigned in doing of it? O how was this above the Power, beyond the compaſs of all the Ordinary Actions of Men! Any one that ſhould have come to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and ſee him prepare to do it, would think, he was ſo far from being Obedient to God, that they would look upon him, as a moſt Frenzick, Diſtracted Man, that had loſt all Underſtanding, and all the Affections of a Father, or, as a cruel and wicked perſon. But Faith fetch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d its Compaſs round about the whole Conſideration of the thing, and Tranſcended all the ordinary Rules, by which Men proceed in their Actions, as ſeeing God giving Chriſt his only Son in it. And ſo <hi>Rahab; ſhe was Juſtified, by ſending the Spies another way:</hi> This was a great Act of Faith: And yet, if it be look'd upon (according as I have ſeveral times mentioned) by the Eye of Reaſon; it was a berraying her own Country. Therefore I ſay, extraordinary, and unaccountable Acts, many times,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104490:35"/> God calls his Servants to, by Faith. When Men come to ſuffer, and to loſe their Eſtates, to loſe all the Enjoyments of their Families, upon the Account of a Principle of the Goſpel; either in Truth of Doctrine, or in Purity of Worſhip; a Man would be ready to think, as of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, they did not underſtand at all, what they did, when they laid down their Lives, upon the denial of that Idolatrous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, of Jeſus Chriſt, being himſelf, Bodily (as they underſtand it) in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And ſo, all along, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. the Heroick Actions of Chriſtians, of the Servants of God, are inſtanced in, as I have inſtanced heretofore to you, in <hi>Moſes:</hi> Men would have thought him one of the fooliſheſt, and ſofteſt Men in the World, when he ſhould <hi>refuſe to be called the Son of</hi> Pharaoh's <hi>Daughter,</hi> v. 28. <hi>And that he ſhould eſteem the Reproach of Christ's greater riches, than the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt; Theſe are extraordinary Acts of Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, as I have ſaid to you. If it had been any of our Caſes at this day, to have <hi>Refuſed to be called the Son of</hi> Pharaoh's <hi>Daughter;</hi> How many Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, Plauſible Appearances of Reaſon ſhould we have to taken up? As, that we might be ſerviceable to the People of God! That we might have done a great deal of good to the Oppreſſed, Afflicted <hi>Iſrael!</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Faith, it fetch'd a compaſs (as I ſay) far above all the general Rules men go by; and ſaw that it was his Duty to do ſo; and <hi>to Eſteem the Reproach of Christ greater riches, than the Treaſures of</hi> Egypt.</p>
            <p>Now, when God does lift up his Servants, and enlarge them beyond the Line of all the Reaſon that is in the World, Therein are Peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Actions of Faith, the great work's of Faith are found there; ſo there are many Caſes in which he works ſo now in the Souls of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The fourth, and laſt kind of the Actions of <hi>Faith</hi> are, in walking by thoſe general agreed Rules of Holineſs, according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which are given us in the word of God, both of the Old, and New Teſtament; they are truly to be called the works of <hi>Faith</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, when men walk in the Commandments of God; <hi>Purifying themſelves, even as God is pure; being Holy in all manner of Converſation.</hi> Theſe are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the works and Actions of <hi>Faith</hi> alſo; So I have repreſented them to you each in their Degree.</p>
            <p>The firſt great Act of <hi>Faith,</hi> is to Unite with Chriſt; and he that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in that, miſſes in all the reſt.</p>
            <p>The Second kind is of thoſe Acts, that Reſult from our continual Application to Chriſt, and his Blood. And then,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the great and Extraordinary Actions God calls his Servants to, when all the world thinks them Mad, and Obſtinate, and the moſt unreaſonable men in the world to do ſo. And yet <hi>Faith,</hi> by that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs that is given to it, it ſees clearly through all. And then,</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104490:35"/>
            <p>Laſtly, Thoſe ſtated Rules of Holineſs, I need not ſhew; becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one knows the proper works of <hi>Faith,</hi> are guided thereby alſo, and the power flows from Jeſus Chriſt by <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come therefore to the Second thing: And that is, the great intereſt Jeſus Chriſt hath in all the great works of <hi>Faith;</hi> and that truly, Chriſt is the <hi>Author,</hi> as well as <hi>Finiſher,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſet forth all the great Examples. <hi>Having ſo great a cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> (v. 1.) <hi>Let us lay aſide every weight,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Looking unto Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith.</hi> All the Actions of <hi>Faith,</hi> they are by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and the <hi>Omega</hi> of all, the Begining and the End of all. And that I would briefly repreſent to you in theſe four things.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this; Becauſe he hath Purchaſed theſe Actions of <hi>Faith</hi> for Believers; or elſe they could never have done them, if he had not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, that they ſhould do them.</p>
            <p>VVe indeed are called to all the Actions of faith, as our Duty; I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it; But it is Jeſus Chriſt that hath Redeemed us to thoſe Holy Actions; or elſe we could never have done them. There are abundant Scriptures that prove this plainly to you. The 2d Chap. of the Epiſt. to <hi>Titus</hi> (for I can but juſt name, and intimate them to you) <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 14. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Who gave himſelf for us, that he might Redeem us from all Iniquity, and purify unto himſelf a peculiar People, Zealous of good works.</hi> All the good works of faith, there is a Purchaſe of Chriſt upon them; Or elſe, they could never have been performed by any of his Saints. And ſo in the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Ye are redeemed from a vain Converſation, by the Blood of Chriſt; That vain converſation, received by Tradition from your Fathers</hi> The Tradition of evil works paſſes uncontrolled, unqueſtioned from hand to hand; and no body but by faith diſputes it, if it comes by Tradition. As you know, the things that are but in faſhion, They run through, not only thoſe that make no profeſſion of the Goſpel, but thoſe that make a profeſſion, ſo Tradition runs through All. Now, how ſhall we be Redeemed from this? There is no way to be Redeemed from the common Evils that are done in the world; but by the precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Second place, as I began to ſay, Chriſt is the great Principle of them. How can you walk in the ways of Holineſs? No way, but by Jeſus Chriſt, being within us, the Principle of thoſe Holy Actions; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, tho I ſay, it is our Duty, and we are condemned indeed, moſt righteouſly in not Anſwering our Duty; Yet ſtill, we cannot do the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Actions required of us, but under a Purchaſe, under a Price. Ye are bought with a Price; therefore glorify God, as the Apoſtle ſaith. And ſo we muſt have that mighty Principle. <hi>I can do all things</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>through Chriſt that ſtrengthens me.</hi> And in <hi>John</hi> 15. Our Lord ſhews plainly, that he is the Principle, <hi>Without me</hi> (ſaith he, v. 5.) <hi>ye can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> He had compared himſelf to the <hi>Vine;</hi> and Believers to the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104490:36"/> 
               <hi>Branches.</hi> Now, as the branch can do nothing without the Vine (you know it cannot) ſo our Souls can do nothing without Chriſt: He is the great Principle of it. And then,</p>
            <p>In the Third place; They are waſhed in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt; And they are all made up in their Imperfections, by the great Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Righteouſneſs and Holineſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, this muſt neceſſarily be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Take that Action of <hi>Abraham;</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, he was <hi>Juſtified</hi> by the <hi>Offering of</hi> Iſaac.</p>
            <p>Naw, I ſay, That very Offering of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, as it was <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Act, <hi>waſhed in the Blood of Jeſus;</hi> or elſe it had never been Accepted. There were (tho we cannot trace them; yet God underſtands them) ſuch Corruptions adhering to this Holy Action of <hi>Abraham;</hi> that if it had not been waſh'd in the Blood of Chriſt, it could not have ſtood before him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rahab ſending away the Spies,</hi> It was waſhed in the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes keeping the Paſſover; and refuſing to be called the Son of Pharaoh's Daughter;</hi> all theſe, they were waſh'd in the Blood of Jeſus; or they could not have ſtood before God.</p>
            <p>All the Repentance, all the Holy Actions of the Beſt, and moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of Chriſtians; they are waſh'd in the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they may be accepted: And wherein they are found Light, they are made up by the Righteouſneſs of our Lord Jeſus <hi>Chriſt. The Righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled;</hi> So I underſtand that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 4. <hi>It is fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit;</hi> That is, by Jeſus Chriſt; as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had ſaid, <hi>He condemns ſin in the fleſh, viz.</hi> His Fleſh, his Sacrifice. And ſo the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled in us,</hi> By all thoſe that <hi>walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. And the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, it makes free from the Law of ſin and Death.</hi> VVhat is the Law of the Spirit of Life in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> But that perfect Righteouſneſs, and that perfect obedience of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, even to the Sacrificing himſelf.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt thing, in which I would ſhew you, that Jeſus Chriſt is ſupremely to be conſidered by every Believer, as the foundation of all his Holineſs, and the Acceptance of it, is this.</p>
            <p>That Jeſus Chriſt is He, through whom alone, and through whoſe perfect Holineſt, God accounts us Holy.</p>
            <p>This, I confeſs, is a Point that is not generally ſpoken of; And it may ſeem to be ſomething ſingular; But <hi>I</hi> am fully perſwaded of it, That we do not only ſtand before God, by Imputative Righteouſneſs, But we ſtand before him by imputative Holineſs alſo; That is, not as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there were no Holineſs Inherent and Real in the Saints of Chriſt, But their Holineſs could not be counted Holineſs, if it were not for the Holineſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104490:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> will not ſtand much upon it; becauſe I know it is a ſingular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: Yet I would give you two Scriptures that do ſtrongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me that this is the very caſe, Till we are brought into the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Holineſs, at the State of the Reſurrection of the Dead: which (as I have formerly told you) is either when Spirits go out of the Body; or when all the Saints ſhall appear in the Reſurrection; then ſhall they be in a perfection of Inherent Holineſs. But while we are here in the World; we are not in a ſtate of Perfect Inherent inward Holineſs. And therefore Chriſt in that (that's the firſt Scripture that enclines me to this Apprehenſion) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>He is made unto us Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and Sactification, and Redemption.</hi> Chriſt is as truly <hi>made to us Sactification,</hi> as he is <hi>made Redemption,</hi> or as he is <hi>made Righteouſneſs</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> in our firſt being brought home to God; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſay, if he not our <hi>Sanctification;</hi> our <hi>Sanctification</hi> could not be looked upon, as <hi>Sanctification,</hi> if it were not made Acceptable by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture is that in the 7th to the <hi>Romans:</hi> Saith the Apoſtle, <hi>We bring forth Fruit unto Death in our ſelves;</hi> He is ſpeaking of <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>Believers;</hi> We bring forth Fruit unto Death, In our ſelves: But when we are <hi>Married unto another, even to him who is raiſed from the Dead;</hi> we bring forth Fruit unto God. We cannot bring forth Fruit unto God (which is certainly meant of Sanctification) any other way, but by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Married to another, even to him who is raiſed from the Dead;</hi> becauſe the Reſurrection of the Dead (in all ſenſe of Scripture) is the Perfection of Holineſs. Till we therefore are in the State of being riſen from the Dead, being in Spirits ſeparated, (as I have ſpoken) or in Bodies of Glory, we cannot bring forth Fruit unto God; but we bring forth Fruit unto Death, if we are not in Chriſt the great Husband, <hi>who is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the Dead.</hi> All our Holineſs is made Perfect by his Holineſs.</p>
            <p>But then he brings us into that Perfection, that every Saint is indeed perfectly Holy, in the ſtate of Spirit, and ſtate of a Body of Glory given to that Spirit, that went out of the Body long (it may be) before, accordlng to the ſeveral times in which the Saints of Chriſt have Dyed.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Third and Laſt thing, which I propoſed in this <hi>Diſcourſe:</hi> And that is,</p>
            <p>To ſhew you what the Senſe of the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> is; for it ſeems to run very Counter to all the Doctrin of Free Juſtification by Faith, and not by Works. It ſeems a wonderful thing, that the Spirit of God, after it had ſaid ſo much by <hi>Paul,</hi> of being Juſtified by Faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works; That the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> I ſay, ſhould ſend out ſo great a Miniſter of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> was, to lay down a Poſition ſo contrary as it ſeems to be to <hi>Paul; That a Man is not Juſtified by Faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, but by Works;</hi> And to make ſo great an Appearance againſt that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104490:37"/> Truh, that great Truth of the Goſpel, and to give occaſion to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Enemies of the Free Grace of God; and to ſo many Devines, and ſtrange kind of Repreſentations of this great Truth, by Men in all Ages, bearing up themſelves, upon the Authority of ſuch a place of Scripture as this is.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, by way of Anſwer to it, I ſhall not be long, altho the thing requires indeed a great deal of Thought and Conſideration. And I hope, God will enable me to give it in ſumm, tho I cannot ſpeak ſo large of it.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing I deſire you to conſider, is; That certainly, upon this great Point, I am very clear in it; We are call'd to Conſider, that if we ſpeak indeed ſtrictly, and down-right to the Point; a Man is no more Juſtified by Faith, as it is a Grace, or an Act, or a Work, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you call it, in it ſelf; I ſay, no more Juſtified by it, than he is by Works.</p>
            <p>Certainly, God would have us fetch about every way, and conſider how this can be, that the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> can ſeem ſo to Contradict the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, The firſt thing that offers it ſelf to us, is, That a man is not indeed Juſtified by Faith, upon any Merit, Excellency, or Worth, or Deſert that is in Faith it ſelf: As I told you, if Faith ſhould pretend to it, it would be thrown, like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> out of Heaven: And therefore, it is not by Faith in it ſelf. And then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, I do believe, that in the ſame ſenſe, wherein Faith is ſaid to be Juſtifying, in dependence upon the Righteouſneſs of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, in the ſame ſenſe, Works may be ſaid to Juſtify, in dependence upon Faith.</p>
            <p>Pray obſerve what I ſay: I ſay, Faith Juſtifies in dependence upon Chriſt; And works may be ſaid to Juſtify in dependence upon Faith. For, in the ſame degree, wherein Faith ſtands to Chriſt for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the ſame degree may works ſtand to Faith, in the matter of Juſtification.</p>
            <p>So that works depend upon Faith, and that depends wholly upon the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. And if this be ſeriouſly conſidered, it will clear to you, what elſe might ſeem a very great doubt.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, to lay down plainly my ſenſe of the Apoſtles ſcope, of being Juſtified by Works, and not by Faith only; There are theſe three ſenſes, in which it may be underſtood: And I ſhall make out every one to you, by plain Expreſſions of the Apoſtle <hi>James;</hi> and yet very briefly, Leaving it eſpecially, to your own Meditation and Thoughts upon it.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:104490:37"/>
            <p>The firſt is this; That wherever a Man is ſuppoſed by the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> to be Juſtified by Works, and not by Faith only; it is, becauſe Faith and Works have a kind of <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> a <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> So, that to ſay Faith, and VVorks, is to ſay no more than to ſay, whole Faith, entire Faith. For, if Faith have not works, it is falſe Faith; it is Counterfeit Faith; it is not whole, entire, true Faith.</p>
            <p>And therefore, the Apoſtle means nothing more by it, than only that; if you would know what Faith you are Juſtified by; it is Faith that hath a Mighty Power of Operation, or VVork: And therefore I underſtand no more by the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> ſpeaking of Works joyned with Faith, than the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>The work of Faith with Power. Faith</hi> hath a mighty Power of working: By <hi>Faith</hi> they did ſo, and ſo, all along, <hi>Heb</hi> 11. This is through Faith; a mighty operating, working faith. And when Jeſus Chriſt gives himſelf, he always gives an operating Faith, ſo he gives himſelf only to a Faith, that he knows hath mighty Power and Principles of Operation; It is, becauſe it is true Faith, whole Faith, entire Faith, the Faith of God's giving, <hi>like precious Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As, you know, in a Jewel; if it be only a counterfeit, it wants ſome of the eſſential Excellencies of a Jewel; As if a Man ſhould think to be made Rich by a falſe Jewel; it is a falſe counterfeit appearance; though it may have ſome appearance of a true Stone, yet it wants the true Exccellency and Value of it.</p>
            <p>So the Apoſtle Diſcourſes, and ſhews, what a true, real, working, juſtifying, operating Faith is, <hi>James</hi> 2. 16. <hi>If a Brother or Siſter be naked, and deſtitute of daily food, and one of you ſay unto him, Depart in peace; be ye warmed, and filled; notwithſtanding you give them not thoſe things which are needful for the body:</hi> You know this is a falſe Charity. And ſo it is a falſe faith, that pretends to believe in Chriſt, and cannot act ſuitably. And again. he faith, <hi>As the Body without the Spirit is dead, ſo Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works is dead alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if we ſhould make a dead Man ſet his hand to a Writing, you know that Writing is of no value; though you may guide the Hand of the dead Man to write ſo and ſo, while you guide the Hand; becauſe he is a Man without Spirit; He has not the Spirit of a Man.</p>
            <p>And ſo Faith, if it hath not all the Graces, and Actions ſuitable to it, it is but a dead Faith. It is dead, as the Apoſtle ſaith; and it is but the faith of Devils. It is not a perfect faith; it hath not truly the Nature of faith; It is not (as I may) the whole Perſon of faith.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Senſe the Apoſtle aimed, and drove at; to diſtinguiſh true faith from a meer formal, profeſſionary faith; ſaying, as Men do, <hi>I believe in one God, the father Almighty;</hi> And ſo, you know, they go on. Now, a meer Profeſſion of Faith, without the power of Faith in a Man's Soul, It is but the counterfeit Image of <hi>faith,</hi> and not <hi>faith</hi> it ſelf; So <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou believeſt there is one God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:104490:38"/>
            <p>In this ſecond place; This indeed, is the way that God doth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally demonſtrate, and manifeſt the Truth of <hi>faith</hi> to the Souls of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and to the Obſervation of others.</p>
            <p>And, ſo it is true, That <hi>faith</hi> cannot demonſtrate it ſelf, either to a Believer's Soul; or (in ordinary and general ſpeaking) it cannot mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it ſelf, except it have Works.</p>
            <p>And ſo, that Senſe that ſome Interpreters give of this Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle here, is, That one Faith juſtifies before God, and the other juſtifies before Men; that is, Faith in its Works, juſtifies before Men; But faith alone, taking Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, before God; though it is always a faith, that hath within it ſelf ſuch a power of Action, as to demonſtrate it ſelf to Men, or elſe it is but a dead Faith: And a <hi>vain Man</hi> it is, that looks upon a faith to be faith, that has not this mighty Operation. And ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Faith wrought with Works:</hi> He does not ſay, His works were alone, but faith wrought with them. That's the ſecond Senſe. It manifeſts, and demonſtrates it ſelf before Men to be Faith. It is that, that juſtifies before a Man's own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, concerning the truth of Faith; and before Men, concerning that real Operation of God upon faith in the Soul.</p>
            <p>Now, to this, the Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak very plainly, in the 18. verſe; <hi>Yea, a man may ſay, Thou haſt faith, and I have works; ſhew me thy faith without thy works, and I will ſhew thee my faith by my works.</hi> You know, this plainly ſpeaks, that faith juſtifies it ſelf before Men, to be true faith, when it ſhews it ſelf in Operations ſuitable to the Nature, and to the Excellency of faith. But, if a Man have no works; if a Man ſays, I believe in Chriſt and be a Swearer, a Drunkard, an impure Perſon; every way unrighteous, and unſuitable to the Commands of God; how can ſuch a Man ſhew his faith? There muſt be an agreeableneſs and ſuitableſs of Converſation, and Action: And ſeeſt thou how faith wrought? It was viſible to Men. And then,</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Senſe, is,</p>
            <p>That faith is daily perfecting it ſelf in holy Action, till it comes to that Perfection (as I have ſpoken before, and ſeveral times, upon the 3<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>Philippians</hi>) till it comes to the Perfection of the <hi>Reſurrection of the dead.</hi> And ſo it fufills the Scripture, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>That is, That whereas it was ſaid before of <hi>Abraham, He believed God, and it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs,</hi> long before he <hi>offer'd Iſaac.</hi> There was not a ſtaying of his Juſtification, till he had offered <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but he was juſtified before he offered <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet faith perfects it ſelf, and <hi>fulfils the Scripture daily,</hi> going on from Grace to Grace, from Strength to Strength; from Degree to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, till it appears before God perfect. And ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>By works was faith made perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:104490:38"/>
            <p>And this is ſuitable to the 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 11. that I named ſeveral times; <hi>That God would fulfil all the pleaſure of his goodneſs, and the work of faith with power; That the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be glorified in you, and ye in him.</hi> Here you ſee it is very plain, That the fulfilling of the good Pleaſure of the Grace of God, it demonſtrates the Truth of Faith, and glorifies the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Believers, and Believers in him; <hi>according to the Grace of our God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Methinks, this very Expreſſion, it ſhould ſilence all the Enemies of the Free Grace of God, and of Juſtification by Free Grace. For, here is as highly ſpoken of the <hi>working of Faith,</hi> as all the Underſtanding of Man can poſſibly reach to; either to conceive, or to expreſs.</p>
            <p>What can be greater, than the Glorifying the Name of the Lord Jeſus in Believers, and Believers being Glorified in him? And yet, all this thrown off quite, from any thing of Man, or Redundancy, by way of Glory, upon Man. It is ſaid, <hi>According to the Grace of our God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now cloſe theſe Things, that I have ſpoken thus narrowly to you (I hope God will enlarge them in your Hearts,) in theſe three brief Applications, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this;</p>
            <p>That you would conſider the infinite Wiſdom of Scripture; Indeed, there is nothing ſo admirable as theſe two Things in <hi>Scripture,</hi> to cut off all occaſion, <hi>to turn the Grace of God into Laſciviouſneſs;</hi> and yet to ſet out the Grace of God, at its full Height and Excellency. O do but take theſe Two Things along, which can never divide nor deceive!</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. All is Grace. And yet.</item>
               <item>2. Grace is mighty in its Operation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And indeed, though we have reaſon to lie low, becauſe Grace as in us ſeems ſo ſhort and narrow in its <hi>Operation;</hi> Yet theſe are two Things that can never be disjoined, They are one within another; It is the Grace of God that brings forth the Holineſs, and keeps it in Union, to Chriſt, even throughout the whole Courſe of a <hi>Chriſtians Life;</hi> and even indeed throughout <hi>Eternity it ſelf:</hi> Grace keeps us in the way of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and new Obedience. <hi>O therefore, let us not turn the Grace of God into Wantonneſs;</hi> And yet, let us be continually admiring, and adoring <hi>free Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us be great Profeſſors of <hi>free Grace;</hi> but, Profeſſors of it, in the Holineſs and Purity of it. And then,</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place; it teaches us ſtill, never to forſake that Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Point of all our Intereſt; of all our Hope, of all the Holineſs
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104490:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> that ever we had, or can have; If we have any at all, we have it from Jeſus Chriſt: He is the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and the <hi>Omega:</hi> He is the Author and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher; He is the <hi>Beginning</hi> and <hi>End;</hi> He is the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Laſt; All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, whenever we deſire to be Holy; <hi>O go to Chriſt, the Redeemer and Finiſher of Holineſs!</hi> Whenever we complain of Corruption, go to him that is able to Redeem from all Iniquity: Whenever we are like to be drawn to vain Tradition, go out to the Precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, who alone can ſet us free from the Power of it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I beſeech you, expect, that there will indeed be a greater State of Holineſs, when that Kingdom of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſhall come into Succeſſion. And, don't think it a long time, becauſe you ſee no more Holineſs yet.</p>
            <p>I would only deſire you to conſider one place of <hi>Scripture</hi> (and with that I will conclude) On what a ſudden God will do this great Thing. The 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 4, 5, 7. <hi>For the Weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God to pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down Imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God; and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Captivity every thought to the Obedience of Chriſt; And having in a readineſs, to revenge all Diſobedience, when your Obedience is fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein the Goſpel, in the Apoſtles Days, for a little time, gave a <hi>Spetimen,</hi> and appearance of it ſelf; Juſt like ſome of the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, that we read of in the World; either <hi>Alexander,</hi> or <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> or <hi>Soliman</hi> among the <hi>Turks;</hi> They paſs'd through the World (as it were) and all lay at their feet: They brought every thing down; As the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks; they <hi>heap'd duſt,</hi> and took every City, and derided every ſtrong Hold, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>As now, the way of <hi>Bombing,</hi> you know, Men go ſuddenly through their Undertaking; In the ſame manner, and much more, ſhall the Goſpel, when once it comes to play its Artillery (as I may ſo ſpeak) through the World; it will open its Magazeen, and carry every thing in the World before it, though they are never ſo ſtrong; and bring every thought, and all into Captivity: And it hath in a readineſs to revenge all Diſobedience; If there be any thing that yields not; it hath a mighty power to Revenge, to bring every thing under.</p>
            <p>And it only ſtays for this; <hi>Till the Obedience of Saints be fulfilled.</hi> Some may ſay, <hi>If we were but more Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God will make us more Righteous, when this time of the Grace of his Goſpel ſhall begin, he will then fulfil in our Obedience.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
